I have no apologies
I was
A crusader
For the development of water
I was the Messiah I was the evangelist
And went out
And argued persuasively
To develop our rivers
And water supplies for the benefit of people
In the American Desert
We have built a great new civilization
In less than a century
Where none could possibly be
In the natural order of things
We have made the land wet where it was dry
And dry
Where it was wet
We have lifted great rivers
Out of their ancient beds and moved them over half a continent
Our great cities stand in a desert that is drier than the
plains Of North Africa
It would all be impossible without the breathtaking manipulation of water
We fought over water thrived on water
And finally
We engineered the desert out of existence
Next to God there's water
Everybody is
Conscious of water
If you headed for the river with a empty bucket you'll likely ever get shot
Can you imagine today
An American city
Acquiring
An entire river
The idea of
Subduing nature
has captivated
the whole
country
Congress cannot appropriate enough money fast enough to build more dams
We built the dams for all the right reasons
When they were desperately needed with little thought to the consequences
The developing world watched and envied our success
The engineering marvel that is Hoover Dam inspected by emperor Haile Selassie of Ethiopia
Supplying water to the population growing that fast is extremely difficult
It was a little bit like the sorcerer's apprentice
You gotta have more water more water more water they're going to
Dam this
Canyon
There was no end to these people who had plans to
dam San Francisco Bay pipelines beyond your wildest dreams when this wasn't about carrying oil
this was about carrying water
We have forgotten that the natural west
is barren
and fatally dry and that our new bountiful west
Is a fragile Construction
Here and there are reminders of what happens when the water is turned off
But when the Water Works fail somehow if the water stops flowing
You'll have a desert again overnight
Well at 6:22 and 7:10
If you see I'm Dominic with AirWatch traffic and I got to tell you the jackknife big Rick
Pasadena has the 210 Eastbound in trouble right at Rosemead where the right three lanes are out of commission
The Jack and I figured there
What about a quarter mile slow
On the westbound side almost
Across the fence from
Right at Sierra Madre
And how are things in Orange County
How do you say
Component Street
Trying to protected by
Vehic
Use alternate routes such
Is Laurel Canyon or even Mulholland
Today
I think my grandfather his Vision was a city like Dublin
Which was the
City of his childhood and it was
A vision I think of a 19th century city
Where people
Ambled
Streets and you they knew one another and
Enjoyed
The theater and the Opera
And the University
A civilized 19th Century City
No other Buick dealership in California has been best in its class
For 7 years
That's because no other Buick dealership is sold more than 10,000 Buick
In the last 10 years the list goes on and on
Right when you have lots of traffic to talk about too
First of all
The thing that you you have to remember about Los Angeles
Never really had a reason
To be there
It had no minerals no Metals no forest
In other words
Everything that
Major
To develop
Itself
LA
lacked
And above all it like
Since the beginning of time this was a place of earthquakes
And Perpetual drought
First Claim by the span
And then conquered by the Americans
Virtually everyone here
I come from somewhere else
In 1878
William o'hallan arrived from the Green Hills of Ireland
It stood away in a sailing ship
Worked at the lumberjack
Failed as a gold miner and had walked across Panama to save $25 in train far
He was fond of one armed chin ups and grand opera
Mulholland found work as a ditch digger on the growing towns dilapidated
Hell I was desperate to become a modern city it had been
Backwater for so many decades
Pretty much the same old Jerry Built thing
Bunch of old water wheel
A falling apart system
He worked hard
Read Shakespeare and Hydraulic Engineering laid into the night entire la
And climb through the ranks
In 1886 when his boss suddenly dropped dead
Will get more Holland found himself superintendent of the LA Water system
The little desert Pueblo had grown to 100,000 people
Thanks to the Chamber of Commerce and a new Railroad
And by 1903
La had sucked dry the tiny Los Angeles River it's only source of water
My mother would tell me these stories
Of growing up without
One bath
A week on Saturday night and I washed and a big zinc tub that was dragged into the kitchen
And water heated
And papa got the first
Your spell mama
And the kids and mother told me you know and they were not
What you call
She told me she never had a bath
in pure clean
Water
I was raised with a real sense that water
The precious item
And not
Squand
Superintendent Mulholland tried to make Los Angeles live within its means
Sabotaged everything he did
By 1903
The chief knew that La would have
Stop growing
Or he would have to find a new source of water
His friend
Mayor Fred Eaton told him of a Great Valley 200 miles to the north
For centuries Paiutes had lived along the Owens River
White settlers who colonized Owens Valley
Found Paiutes irrigating natural grasses with several miles of small irrigation canals
My grandmother told my oldest sister that when the lights came they started
To push the Indians up into the
Rocky
Places where the water
was scarce
Because they wanted the water
For for their cattle
And
And they came in and they fenced everything up
What's everything
They started saying if you want use my water you have to have special permission and Indians always like the water run
It was never
It's something that belonged to one individual person it belong to the whole community
By 1904
Settlers from New England
Switzerland and Scotland had taken the Indians land
Established farms in a dozen towns and a steamboat service on the age-old Owens Lake
They dug an elaborate irrigation system diverting the Owens River into
Hundreds of miles of ditches
Former mayor Fred Eaton convince Mulholland to set out Northwood across the
Mojave Desert in the fall of 1904 toward Owens Valley
They went by buckboard
Which was the only way you could go it took them about 2 weeks to get there
I think there was a trail of whiskey bottles all the way out
In 2 weeks
Mulholland and Eaton were on the banks of the Owens River
At certain times of year in wet years anyway
You can get a little glimpse of what
The river must have been like then
And how it must have impressed Mulholland
The Owens
Valley is one of the most dramatic places in the world
You have on the one side
The Sierra Nevada
Virtually every Mountain over 14,000 ft
And then you have
A drop of
two miles
To the valley
Floor
And then a rise of
almost 2 miles up
To the white mountain range because
The mountains
Stop virtually all weather there is no rain in Owen's Valley
It is in the
And there's no rain in the Owens Valley it is
True desert
Looking
On
Snow cover
And through the middle of it comes
What you almost could call it
Mississippi River
Setting
It is so improbable
Desert
To see a river
That used
As in
And
Not only was this a river
That
Take care of
The
He probably
Population
La
But
Flow all the way
By
Funny
First time
And back so full of enthusiasm he says you know I've seen something here as water that'll
Into the next
And I think about Holland suddenly
Must have changed
And he saw himself
As a sort of
Builder of a Roman Masterwork
Is somebody who
Kept
Great hydraulic
Engineering
Traditional
I can't tell you what went through his head but suddenly he was a convert
Having been more of
An efficiency guy at a conservationist suddenly he became
Empire builder
Almost overnight
They were going to capture a river the only river that kind of accidentally flow
To this desert and they were going to move the whole river
Across
200 plus miles of terrain
Cover that some risk probably to their
The problem facing Mulholland
Was that the river was
Was old all the water
We're owned by Farm
So irrigating something like 60,000 Acres
This was
Driving agricultural area
Time and it was being further developed
By the beer Rec
The how in the world were you going to rest that water away from these farmers
And the federal government
That was
Can you imagine today
American city
Acquiring
An entire River
For its
Course
It goes without saying it couldn't be done but it was done then
Posing his agents for a federal project meant to irrigate Owens Valley
Mulholland's men went to the county courthouse
There they convinced clerks to show them Deeds
Maps and records of streamflows
Within days
Eden was quietly buying property and water
Not to a local irrigation project
But to the city of Los Angeles
Without telling Mulholland
Former mayor Fred Eaton bought the only damn side of Owens Valley for himself
City New
Who
The best water
Who was likeliest Sal
It was
Didn't take very long
For them to capture most of that River
Two people who would
Ultimately benefit
And who knew the whole story of
Where the Publishers of the Los Angeles Times
Harrison gray Otis and Harry Chandler
They were the big
Promoters and boosters but they were sworn to secre
As this was going on they did not let the cat out of the bag
Until they couldn't help
And finally under a bed
The Titan
Project to give the city a river
They talked about how the whole thing had gone
And
You know what I mean when you read that today and imagine a major city newspaper
Just kind of gloating over the trium
Of
You know it's
Artifice
It
You're
In a sense but that was
What Los Angeles was liking
It was
The climate was one of
Of
Getting what you want
Anyway
The Owens Valley Paper saw the future differently
The still secret Aqueduct route
Would pass through the San Fernando Valley on its way to LA
And someone was buying up near worthless land in the San Fernando
Now
Another cat out of the bag
It was a real estate Syndicate that would make millions of Owens River water irrigated their newly acquired San
Fernando Valley land
What was happening
All the while these water
The Owens Valley
Requirement was at the San Fernando Valley
You being
Stop by a cynical
Who represented
Power structure of Los Angeles
What kind of exquisite
Sense of proportion
Incest
If Jonathan Club California
Oh boy
Wasp Network
Dogs black
Mexicans alive
Was bought
By
First capitalists of Los Angeles
For the purpose
Of irrigating it
But it Owens River finally arrived
Because Los Angeles wouldn't need all that water for a long time
If water could be brought
The San Fernando
From the Owens Valley
That rangy grassland
Send me arid terrain could be turned into
Absol
With all the cats out of all the bag
Listens with now vote on the
Mulholland campaign with a vengeance
Secretly
But in the middle of a drought
With the temperature climbing toward 105
The people of La voted 10 to 1 to pay for mulholland's aqueduct to bring them the river they
I think one thing that gets overlooked when does in discussing the
That it was
A popular
Move
From the president of the United
States down to the voters
In the city of Los Angeles
Highly approved
Project
President Theodore Roosevelt deciding the greatest good for the greatest number
Made Owens Valley off limits to further development
By surrounding it with a national forest
It's only became part of the Indio National Forest the only National Forest in America would hardly any trees
The only trees were the orchard trees that were being irrigated and were about to die
With the law and the president on his side
Mulholland set out in 1905
To build his Aqueduct across the desert
It was a great drama it was a great epic drama the building of that aqu
You have mule teams and you have men
They were working in Des
Arid conditions
Water was a problem ironically enough here in this giant water project
They had to worry about adequate water for
The working stock and the men
It can be almost freezing it at night and then 110° in the day
I'm practically Muhammad's there
All the time
Chief engineer Mulholland had no formal training in civil engineering
He had in fact never graduated from grade school
We're still Sail
And this was an engineering project the likes of which the world had really
Mulholland ordered 12 ft steel pipe forged in Germany and shipped around the horn
100,000 men and women worked on the aqueduct
But never more than a few thousand at a time
Because the exhausting and dangerous work
They have been Farm hands Cowboys
And hard rock miners
But now they were city employees
Civil servants like the chief himself
With air conditioning no Refrigeration no hard hats
110° Heat
They crossed the Mojave in 5 years
Locomotive
You know an aqueduct
That would have
All the way across
Massachusetts
And then almost all the way back
Through a desert
With
What they were really building was was the world's longest Garden
Surveyor said they could build the aqueduct simply by following the trail of whiskey
Board in 1904
In the end the chief and his lieutenants finished the
Will Holland built
The original Aqueduct so well
After this day it's still carries the Owens River
To the people of Los Angeles
The phrase Grandpa's aqued
That's where my my first
The day of the dedication of the aqued
Without
About the high point of my grandfather
Is life
Problem 30 to 40,000 Los Angeles that gather at the base of
There's a formal program
But once the water spilled down the Cascade the formal program was abandoned
Because thousands of people rushed with their 10 cups to drink the water
When the water came cast getting down there
One who was really exhausted
Gave what I think is the most
Precise education speech and
He unfurled an American flag
He turned to the water
And he said
There it is
Based on mulholland's predictions it was four times more water than Los Angeles could use
Oh so slow Parkway if you're on the San Diego South at Magnolia that accident cleared to the right shoulder we're clear back
To the Westminster Mall with Bumper to Bumper to the beach cities
And if you could be
Actually has to be seen not just in terms of human
However brief human history
Has to be seen in terms of geological
Local time
Do you have for the eons
An environment
Now being
Found
Change by the changing course of that River
And that water
In effect
Created
Contemporary Los Angeles
It's your earthqu
This week at last subjects to Honolulu
SunTrust your pipeline to Paradise
Would I watch traffic celebrating this
Great event
He
Need a speech
Made the very
The observation he said
We're doomed to success
Might be a motto for
The city don't you think
When water came after 1913
It prepared for an absolute golden age of building and construction
That lasted through the
At one point in the early twenties there was some 67
Lumber ships at the San Pedro Harbor lined up just waiting to get the
The wood off so they could keep the construction going
You also have the beginnings of the great Hollywood fig
So coming out DW Griffith
Success will be Dem
Coming just a few months after the water
At nowhere As you move to Los Angeles will you not in the presence of Lawns edges
Palm trees
Great palm trees which sway above Los Angeles now like nodding giraffes
Here you had a semi-arid region
Were coyotes roamed were Tumbleweed is blown by the wind
Which in a very short
Was turned into arguably the most Exquisite invented Garden history
Now if you like that
With the adjacent citrus
Which we're still in full bloom and then teens in the 20s
I wasn't there
You had a general sensibility of that time of turning the
Desert into an Eden
Charlie Chaplin and Aldous Huxley came from England
William Faulkner from Mississippi
Frank Lloyd Wright from Wisconsin
Everyone came from everywhere
Ballet was suddenly growing 11 times faster than New York
Faster even than Calcutta
A million people by 1922
At home 31,000 were licensed real estate agent
Now
Over mulholland's objections
Los Angeles began annexing 52 surrounding communities
Soon the city limits would cover 400 square miles
More than any city in America
Going to be a lot of irate citizens when they find out
You're paying for water
Not going to get oh that's all taken care
What is simply meant was
You
You would bring the water to where
You wanted to bring
And call that place la
And and and therefore
You can get Los Angeles
Taxpayers
To pay
What in
A cabal of Real Estate speculators
To
City
Pay millions of dollars for them to pump water down to land that was not in fact part of the city and then caused them to
Hope that is part of
And thereby increase the value of that language they had purchased and held
So they were causing
One city in
To pay for them to develop another city by car and then say well it's really the same city
As the Owens River was finally
Being relocated
Quarter of the State of California
It it became
Immediately obvious
Yes
There was way more water than Los Angeles
And
Because the water was coming into the sand Fernando Valley it ended up irrigating
San Fernando
I was basically an artificial important river
For agriculture
We're there rather than
The agriculture that had been
Tracks in the San Fernando Valley
Blossomed into orange and Lemon Grove
Peach or
Fields of winter tomatoes
By 1920 LA County was the most productive Farm County in America
It may have been
But to move a whole river ostensibly for public good and end up
Making
A bunch of
Capitalists even richer than they already were
By giving them
A brand new
Was really a kind of a remarkable
Everything you can say everything around us I was at the hall of records today the original
Title for Chinatown
I
Just going to call it Water and Power
No that's what it came in and water was
Power
It was
It was money
And those who knew how to manipulate it
Alexa much more than anybody could ever manipulative
And you could say it
It was a
Running through your movie
Just a river of greed
Do you have any idea what this land would be worth with a steady
Supply
About 30 million more than they paid for it
The Syndicate began plowing under their newly developed San Fernando orange groves for tract homes
Advance guard of the largest subdivision in history
The value of their land had gone
Tenfold
This is a great age of salesmanship because these were masters of the art
I've encouraging people to Envision
On an empty Hillside the great cities the towns
The schools the churches the synagog
Which would one day be there
Have they but the faith that the salesman had
Owning your own home in this region
Was given an almost quasi religious
Value
That your children will not be delinquent if you had a home that your marriage would be happy but many of the ills of our society were due
The fact that the people lived in cities and rented
Mulholland himself did not profit directly from the syndicates dealings
But he was now the highest
Paid Public Employee in California
The University of California gave an honorary degree to Dr Mulholland
The penniless immigrant
Who never finished grade school
But could keep the entire LA water system in his head
La now had a Mulholland School
Mulholland
Mulholland Reservoir
And named its new winding Scenic Drive
Every kid in Hawaii
No it was one of the first names you learn when you when you hit the
When you're old enough to get a junior operator's license because that's where you parked your car to make
Until now
Once association with my
Hey
The man in the family
A staple of conversation water work
There was always a Dodge to
The family
Pick up to go out it was just easier to see the wildflowers in the spring but
It somehow always ended up that we were standing in front of some big
Turbine or Waterworks
With the men discussing
On just the way
You know I
I discuss impressionist paintings with a friend at the County Museum
The city which never had a reason to be now had a thousand oil
It's on automobile and airplane factories
And before long
90% of all the world's movies would be made in LA
The imported Owens River
Allow the city to expand at three times the rate Mulholland had used in his aqued
Calcul
It wasn't a profit
And that's what upset a lot of the balance
Assistance committee tried to nominate William
He said he would rather give birth to a porcupine backward than the mayor of Los Angeles
It was a scramble I mean the city kept growing and the Chamber of Commerce kept booming and there were always
Marvelous come on from
To the railroad companies and from the Chamber of Commerce and he he used to joke and say that he thought
The only thing is to stop LA from growing
Kill Frank wig
And Frank Wiggins with the president of the Chamber of commer
To spend his lifetime booming La all over the country
And encouraging more people
And so it was a little bit like The Sorcerer's Apprentice you start
The process going
And you got to have more water more water more water and you the father of the city's water system
Are supposed
What's the continue to provide this water
It's a terrible place to be
And you've got to be ingenious and inventive and come up with
New
We're getting water
Now there were 60,000 Realtors
The Chamber of Commerce said millions of promotional brochures to the Midwest and New England to Guatemala City
Paris
Only 10 years after Mulholland finished his great Aqueduct with a four-fold surplus
La was running out of water
And he was pondering new sources
The Colorado
Mono Lake
Or the sier
Maybe the best example of the metamorphosis of Mulholland into an
Excessive water Seeker was described to me
Of course
Who was
Back in
20 superintendent of Yosemite National Park
And he was at the banquet table with mulholl
And mul
Started waxing
Eloquent about how beautiful
The valley is
And then I said
What he would do
If he
If he would send phot
Photograph
All day long
All
Every season
And just have
The most
Astounding collection of
Yosemite photograph
But you could ever imagine
Put them in books
And send them free to every library in the world
And then
He would go in there
And build a great big Dam
And stop the
La Rivals San Francisco was in fact planning a dam
Which would soon permanently submerge hetchy
Under 300 ft of water
Owens Valley had in fact gotten off easy compared to Hitachi
The southern half of the valley
Leaving the northern Townsend Farms to flourish during World War I
Well Owens Valley was an absolute team I'd say show
Produced
Over to get this fruit from here
I can remember when the sky would get black with flights to duck this was one of the major flyways
Absolutely black with him I mean that the sky would be black and even for a day or two
More for hours and hours
There's a great
Time to live up here it was a very close-knit Community him
Every Saturday night that keep you up for house open all night and they had
Show the movie when the movie is over they push the chairs back and everybody dance to all night
Then it have a breakfast and everybody go home back to the ranches it said something up you know
Did this every Saturday night and it was a great time to live and the only Valley
What few people knew was that William Mulholland was about to turn his attention
To what remained of the Owens River
This growing city of Los Angeles
Becomes like a vampire
Making a direct
Connection to the major artery of the Owens Valley which is the Owens River
And of course imagine those Ranch
Los Angeles will be there partner their friend that they would grow and prosperity along with the city
Began to see that the vampire was sucking the lifeblood and that
Fertile feels for becoming parched and non productive
In the wet years since 1905 relations between the city and the valley had been surprisingly cord
But now there was drought
The city song 52 turbine Wells into the valley floor
To pump ground water into the aqueduct
Crippling surrounding ranches
But people resented here they didn't have the option they didn't have a choice
And the pressure that build over 20 years and the way it was done
And this whole water we're talking about
Yeah they could care nothing about this property
On Sunday my mother would take me for
And she would always talk about
Apple orchard
And teach
And it wasn't till years later
That I realize because growing up in Bishop
There was always we were surrounded by sagebr
It was always dry it was always testy
There's always dust in the air
And
Couldn't even imagine what my mother was talking about I couldn't imagine
And it took me until a young adult to real
It was much different at one time
I would have liked to have seen
What my grandparents
I'd like to see the
It must have been gorgeous
I must have been gor
I mean I think that
50 Owens Valley
It's beautiful
I grew up there
And it's beautiful now so can you imagine what it was like
When my grandfather
When my great-grandfather
They can make me cry
Anger mounted as mulholland's men cut ranches canals
The city bought more land - more and more water half the crops were gone the 1924
Schools and businesses began to close
Owens
Went bone dry
Rumors of resistance began to fly
Someone blew a hole in the siphon
And then
Just before Thanksgiving in 1924
The local bank president and 100 citizens
Seize the aqued
They open the floodgates
And sent the entire flow of the Owens River down a ditch
They organize
Model T's that
Probably dozens of cars
Down to the Alabama Gates
On the aqueduct
Where there was a turnout Val
Where they could basically stop the flow of water to Los Angeles
Talk about Community involvement
I know that my grandfather was there
I have spoken recently with my
Mother
Cous
And she said that she remembers that it was a party
That her mother
Got her up early
And got her
And she was only four
So
There is
I mean that was a
And those people didn't move from the Alabama Gates they didn't move
I took a lot of Courage I did
So there was a whole bunch of
Four arbitration but discussion but interest-focused on this thing is mainly what they were after
The crowd
Singing on with Christian Soldiers
Playing Enrico Caruso when a hand cranked phonograph
Superintendent Mulholland sent City police to take back the water
But the local sheriff stood between the officers and the citizens
This news did travel around the world this was
It's a great big story
And it was embarrassing
Los Angeles
Because they were being cast as the villain and you know it was hard to see them any other way
Mahogan saw this is number one in instance of civil interaction
But saw that nothing less than the survival of Los Angeles itself was at stake
And it basically
There had to be a cleansing of a farmers from that region
That the
Communities were incompatible
And that they would have to be bought out
And so they decided to try to sit down with some of the leaders of the Owens Valley and negotiate
Some kind
After a week
The local bank president told the Raiders that a Los Angeles Consortium would negotiate a fair price for the remaining
Water rights in Owens Valley
La would even consider sharing the water
With cheers and congratulations
Only to learn later
That the deal had fallen through
As
Negotiations such as they were are going on
The city is
Visually buying more
Rights Land and Water right
In the
Basically
Find the whole
While Ranch is occupied the aqueduct
City agent
Secured legal options on virtually all remaining land and water rights in Owens Valley
They bought whole towns
Even the county seat and County Jail
More
And it's not the first time either
The last bombing was 4 years ago
Property
I
It's one of the main line
About 150 miles north of Los Angeles
That Supply is water to the Big Town
It's lucky Los Angeles has an emergency watershed
For this might have resulted
In a terrible drought disaster
The police are after the fiends who did this rotten
Let's hope they get
There's no pun
Too strong for
Give received a phone call
This is like
Telling Leonardo da Vinci that someone's just slashed the Mona Lisa
When he was
Appalled outraged and
Furious
Point
A certain
Ugly
Turn
Occurred the mood
Now
Night after night
Saboteurs Dynamite at mulholland's master walk
The great aqueduct
Ultimately depend
We had
Numer
Stories about my grandfather
Take it
And blowing up
Dynamite
The aqu
Pride in
Active
Of the mini r
Tomorrow if
There we go along and andynam
Sections and then it go right
Back up into the Hills
Would camp out for weeks and weeks and
After they had bonded
They were afraid to come home and
How
Their wives and kids had to basically hold
Whole family in Fort together
But could never win a single conviction
Heroes down in your own mind now those guys are
April they did and
And we wish we'd been there if we were kids you know
Interestingly enough then he went on to be
California state Sen
So he
Listen to Crazy Man
He was just a man on a mission and a
Mulholland and
Colleagues
Said look this is
This can't go on
This is
Threatening the
Your supply for a great City
This is Criminal
And they sent machine guns up there and
Trailers of them
We're going up to the Owens Valley
And basically imposing martial law
There were searchlights and flood lights up and down that Valley
Sweeping across the aqueduct
All night long
Mulholland
600 heavily armed police
To secure the city's water supply
Backed by the full force of state and federal law
Endorsed by the Chamber of Commerce
As German war said
Everyone has his
And I'm sure he had his reason
I can see how it would have been very easy to get carried away
Powerful
See what you can do
City
The Great
Why is it kidding he was
He was a bad guy he was the guy with the black hat he was
Hated him you know and we all
Talk about him a lot of evil guy was but
He had
Fant
Division
But he didn't care who stepped over to get it
He didn't care what happened to the orange valley girl it was not good
But to be a Mulholland and Owens Valley
I was never taken there
And my folks if they should chance
The travel my mother told me they always
Register to the hotel
Using her maiden
Because
We were
Well
It's in Owens Valley and it was not a good name
To carry
It was a very honest
Because he said that everyone in Bishop was the son of a b****
And
There wasn't enough pine trees to hang the natives on which they deserved
Where is the rest of
They went
A protocol and was invitation and so on but not Mulholland he knew that
It was a vein
Hope I mean to think that they could go back
The water been taken it was the Fatal complete there was no turning back
Owens Valley was not
Going to
Be reverted back to what it had been in 19
That
Been done
Somebody did put up a sign then that said Los Angeles City
Way out in the Owens Valley
It was really
That everyone knew William mulholl
He had won the valley
Before long
City bulldozers began knocking down farm houses and filling in irrigation ditch
Well first we
The valley
Then the settlers came in and took it away from us
Then the city of Los Angeles came and they took it away from them
All Mulholland needed now was a place to store water for the growing City
But former LA mayor Fred Eaton
On the only Reservoir site in Owens Valley
And was demanding a million dollars for it
Thermal Holland built a huge dam in the Hills just 40 miles from downtown LA
It was the largest
Support Dam in North America
The final Link in a decade of trium
By the spring of 28
The reservoir in San Francisco Canyon
Was full to the brim with a year's supply of Owens River water
Far from the scene of battle
On March 12th
Workers noticed a small leak on the north side
Mulholland inspected the Le
Pronounced the damn sound and went home to bed
My grandfather was awakened from his sleep
With a phone call
Saying the dam is gone out
And his first
Responses he stumb
Towards the phone
Let's oh please God
Don't let people
Be killed
There was no warning
There was no warning system
And it started wiping out whole commun
You
So much water
In that damn that there
Thousand
Concrete
Riding the crest
It was
Not water
At a certain point it was trees
Blocks of concrete Rock
Rubble it was a semi-sol
Advancing
20 or 30 mph
I was five years old from
Francis
Broke
And
With my limited perceptions I real
Have some
Beautiful thing it was like bringing a dark curtain down over
Alight
Area
My father took me
He was my father was
Stand and he took me in the car
My mother was not well
Set the time
And we drove up to
The damn
And on the way up
He taught me how to say San francisquito
Canyon
And we rehearsed it over and over
As if it works some kind of
Catechism lesson and what it did for me was in print
Name forever
My mind as a scene of
Some terrible fate
It should be full on our family
Mulholland surveyed the greatest man-made disaster in California history
His Saint Francis Dam
I killed as many people as the San Francisco earthquake
I've always been moved all my life
At the pictures that were taken
Of in the morning that he went up and surveyed
The ru
I said of the damn failure
It's like looking at
Strict in human being I have ever seen it's a
Stark look on his face as he stands amid the rubble
Something he had created
There's an engine
Horrible say any engineer could have
To build a structure that fail
And also
Grandma Holland was in the State of Shock
He he made an initial
Effort really it wasn't much of an effort to blame the whole thing on Dynam
Here's which was the term he not used generically to refer to
Anybody in the Owens Valley
But it was soon very obvious
Put the damn had
By itself
And nobody had sabotaged it
And that Mulholland had had paid a visit
To the dam just
Hours earlier
And I said
It was fine
So his
Which
He had been a
In Los
Mulholland went from being
The father of the city
Founder of the city
To standing possible indict
The precise cause was never found
No criminal charges were over filed
But the coroner's jewelry held William Mulholland responsible
He accepted the blame
Broke down in sobs and said that he
Envy the Dead
Slowly taking away the water
On the canal
Send the ditches and everything in slow
But surely you know they got everything siphoned down and so the land
The trees and no
Upstairs they all Dale died
All the orchard died off and they're all gone
Vanilla house are
They just turned back
Into the desert if it was basic
When we traveled to Los
Sweet
The
My parents would always say
There's our water
Girls that water came from feeling
And as
As a child I remember feeling animosity towards
Los Angeles
You always knew you always
They took our
The Holland resigned in disgrace
His real achievements clouded by the disaster and by the suffering in Owens Valley
His plans were still greater aqueducts lay on the drawing board
But do the people of LA
He was an embarrassment
Officials begin referring to the Mulholland Reservoir
As the Hollywood Reservoir
Owens Valley was history
But fantasy and folklore lived on
The myth of rampaging bullies destroying a paradise
Dallas ranchers defending their homes
The new Valley has been condemned
What do you mean
Turn the volume to a reservoir
It's going to be built whether you like it or not
In 1934 using mulholland's original plans
The Metropolitan water district blasted a new aqueduct
All the way to the Arizona State Line to its second river
The Colorado
To bring in water from an outside sour
Against the serious water short
A water source capable of supplying our
Is the Colorado River
The governor of Arizona deployed his State militia to The Rivers Bank
To stop Los Angeles from taking Colorado River water
It was to no avail
Final resolution would not come until 30 years later
After one of the longest court cases in American history
On the day when the Waters of the Colorado River rushed through the attack with us
The greatest engineering speed of its kind never accomplished we'll take his place among the wonders of the world
It is a wonderful thing to contemplate
This new con
Of the Great Southwest
For everything that man desires
This
Everything except sufficient water
Where's sufficient water
We can be assured
Have a great
And a stable civilization
Wow what a day
I'm afraid we're going to be busy hi Greg it was a high speed Pursuit earlier this morning
Investigation but for the bumper to
He brought enough elements together
Water
Well
So that Los Angeles was now almost condemned
To grow
After
The 1920s
Los Angeles's history is almost
Define
By
Obsess
Search for more and more water
Hoover Dam
Authorized in 1928 finished by the mid 30s
Then mono
Which is a north of the Owens Valley
Was hooked up to the aqueduct
And begins reading all the streams that feed this
Irreplaceable natural wonder out there
Mulholland had long had his eye on mono
100 miles north of Owens Valley
In 1936
His successors dusted off his plans and pushed the aqueduct North to Mono
Speaking again the greatest good for the greatest number
People really shouldn't have any problem with our water system and take it for granted or the water people aren't doing their
How I felt that I was working for a good Purp
I wasn't
Doing something that in my view
Really didn't basically benefit
Society
I felt that I was working on something
Was it was a fundamental benefit
Society I was proud
The people of La could now depend on water from ancient streams
Feeding mono
This is the desert this is the Grim waterless waste that covered most of Los Angeles
Make the most of their mild seductive crime
Optimism
The rise of Nazis in Germany
Have the creation of a Euro Southern California
Auto preminger who is the course playing the Nazis
Was at the Hillcrest Country Club
And people
Playing
People were talking and these two people start talking and Hungarian
And they're talking with hungry and not a promise you said
What's the
She said talk German
From Berlin New York Alabama from
All over the world people flooded into Southern California
They said it was just like everywhere else
Only more so
It's something like that
That's not like
You know love and good
But he really miss it by its
It's very
This wasn't aware I was never aware growing up
Wonderful it was
Until it was
Gone and that was the air it
The air was wonderful
But he's stopping think about
Temperature of
The climate here year-round
Probably
The most perfect limit
With almost no clothing
Is it
The
But it's almost an extension of your own skin it
God is not too cold
The Machinery of water acquisition overworked the Owens River
Colorado and the mono basin
In 1964 the Metropolitan water district proposed diverting the Columbia River to Southern
California
The future had arrived
Somebody finally decided
Rather than
Just go after another sour
Of water
Every 10 or 20 years why don't we go
To where there's so much water
We'll have enough for 200
And where was that
Alaska
It would have brought
This water down in Hu
Irrigated Nevada irrigated Eastern Oregon on the way
Some of it would have gone all the way to Mexico it was going to go to Arizona it was going to go to
Nobody
Really BL
There were lots of people in the business who thought well yeah
Maybe a little premature but this is going to happen
But rather
Preview of an atomic Marvel
I love tomorrow
Stone in men's development
A nuclear powered agro-industrial complex with a nuclear reactor as the
Cheese
Industrial complex
They were plans the last two
You know what
Iceberg
I'm down
You know it was like the flim-flam man I mean there was no end to these people who had plans
The damn San Francisco
Francisco Bay
Pipelines Beyond Your Wildest Dreams
This one this wasn't about carrying oil
This was about carrying water
This is this is water
Chris at the time
Nobody was
Challenging the idea of
Using 8 gall
Of water
Prof
To the toilet
Irrigating your law
To the point where it's standing an inch deep in water
Nobody thought about conservation
The city had long since exhausted Supply from the tiny Los Angeles River
And cemented over its Channel by 1960
The DWP built a reservoir to store a supply of Owens River water near the center of
Los Angeles
The Los Angeles city police helicopter is here the Los Angeles City Fire Department helicopter is here
Police are on the ground with motorcycles and automobile trying to effectively activate people from here
So they can't possibly be any more loss of life than there is property no telling how much property
Has already been lost triangle shaped
Reservoir
The department of order and power had no choice but to carry on
Since it now served
3 million people
In 1966 La acquired its Third River
Like a giant version of mulholland's Owens Valley Project
The California state Aqueduct now brought the Feather River from 600 miles north
Enough water to fill the Rose Bowl
Every 90 minutes
Los Angeles
By the '70s was reaching
200 mi in One Direction 250 mi in another Direction and 600 MI
In a third
For water
It still
Enough
In 1970 the Department of Water and Power
Using mulholland's original sketches
Finished the second Barrel
Sucking now twice as much water from Mono Lake
Logan year old Lake now fell to feed every year
It was the only stop for a million migrating seabirds
On their way from the Arctic to Bolivia
We can see the light going down and down and then I'm pretty sure it wasn't anything growing around the lake anymore
Everything was drying up all
Springs were dying
You know that was that was really
Devastating because we thought
The whole lake is going to be
And
When you think of God's given like you think it should be like it was
The local people had already resigned themselves to the fact that the lake was going to dry up or get to a very small level
Just because of the adversary Department of Water and Powers too big to fight it was not
Anything that anybody could do great Alkali dust storms begin boiling up off the exposed
Hours of mon
And the dry bed of Owens Lake
A 1974
Owens Valley
The Switzerland of America had the worst particular pollution in the country the
Since
Somehow La had thinned
Against
Another
People
Became a central imagery in this whole water story
And one that I've always
Have a lot of
Of trouble with
Because I've always
Sympathize with the underdog
At the same time I've been proud of my grandfather so it's giving me a great deal of conflict
I have
Come to term
Without
Why are you doing it
How much better can you eat what can you buy
You can already afford
The future
And the
In the name of the future
Against the future
It's really the
California
Is the Supreme IR
Face the
The right time in the right place they're capable of somet
There's some some
Monsters
Figure out how to punish
So
They actually sort of reward
Let me know
On the scenic route of the city
My family's names are on
Tax
So they found
Rather than in jail where they're
But I think a movie like Chinatown is an easy out
It oversimplifies its melodramatic
It's not true
I mean not literally
But it provides a rather easy
Explanation
And for people who like to bash la
It's perfect
New York
Hold it up with a piece of his
The movie Chinatown Was Bad contorted history
But it was powerful my
Rekindling violence against the Department of Water and Power
Now headquartered in a building that cost as much as mulholland's original aqueduct
There was violence here before a long time ago
Back in 1924 angry farmers and ranchers line the wall
Armed with shotguns and rifles
They blue holes in the aqued
This year it took
This
A dynamite blast at the gates of the first aqueduct
The water for Los Angeles stopped
Briefly
And the population of bish
More in fact than the entire population of Owens Valley
But this time
Something had changed
David Gaines
A young biologist from LA and a dozen University of California students
Had begun a careful study of mono Lakes singular ecosystem
They found it on the brink of collapse
We knew about Owens Lake of course no just a dry
You know 100 miles to the South and we realized I didn't want to like could look like that someday and
Once you realize what was here that all that would be
To
Couldn't let it
Just go down without making some effort to save it
Mono Lake had fallen 40 f
Exposing mineral Towers which had formed underwater over the ages
It had become three times saltier than the ocean
What we are asking
Asking what Mona Lake is asking all of us is where are we going to draw the line
If we don't
Share some water with Mono Lake what will be next will it be like Tahoe will be the Eel River the Yukon
Will it be on and on until the last of our singing rivers and beautiful lakes are gone
Because we've taken every last drop
We've watched the last waterfowl
The last salmon
Follow the California state emblem the California grizzly into Oblivion
It is a Battleground in that sense
It's asking us
How much are we going to share with the Earth
Primitive
I mean
12 people only one or two cars everybody else did their research
Be
They take their binoculars in their backpack and their lunch and hop on their bikes and they'd ride down the dirt roads and
Dump their bikes and Hike out for a couple miles
Going to walk through mud and
They were really the
Quintessential
Researchers out there
Braving the elements
I got big beards
And so
Mr Gaines he was one of them y'all
He looked just like
The rest of your
I like it kind of like a hippy I'd say but I don't want to say
But he
It's pretty smart that guy
It started things going here
When I grew up in Los Angeles I never learned where water came from
And it was only after doing some complex calculations that we learned that if diversions
This Lake will fall another 40 to 60 vertical feet
What we will be left
Up with
Is an Alkali Wast
A sterile chemical sump where there is now one of the most
Beautiful
And life productive
This is on Earth
Far more than natural beauty was threatened at Mono Lake
What was at stake was
A big
Aquatic ecosystem is very simple but very productive I mean the numbers are astronomical you got
And then the brine shrimp
Ethiology and then you've got millions of birds coming every summer
Keith O'Brien flies in a brine shrimps
Dream was out there
But I don't think we
We gazed up at it too much it might be too discouraging
I mean to have a handful of biologist
Fighting the Department of Water and Power of the city of Los Angeles with a multi-million dollar
Budget
Was too big of a contrast
When William Mulholland took water from Owens Valley and Mono Lake years before
No one questioned the dam
To Nature
But an environmental movement had come of age in America
Along with powerful new law
And a great shift in public opinion
Committees at Mono Lake and Owens Valley
Went to court
To stop the water Conquest Mulholland had said in Motion in 1905
If you're angry and have nothing
No other recourse
I think Dynamite comes to mind
And they were ranchers they understood Dynamite we were College biologist
No experience with Dynam
We knew facts and figures and we knew that we could you know we're educated people and we could probably figure out how
Find lobbyists to go
To help us in Sacramento and how to find lawyers
People are saying well ask for a lot at go way high and then you compromise down with the politicians and the agencies and
We are all biologist because I said
It doesn't sound right
Why can't we just start with what we know is the truth
And just stay there forever
And that's what we did
The Court's rule that drying out the Owens River or streams feeding Mono Lake
Was not in the public interest
In 1988
Force the city to return water to Mono for the first time in half a
Los Angeles began water conservation on a scale never before seen in America
And now shares the water in a fragile piece
With Owens Valley
And mono
Local person said
If you guys save the lake I'll eat my hat
It turns out that we've saved the lake and we have the regulations and people seem much happier BC water running down the
Make fish in the creek
Maybe some of them remember
The great numbers of ducks and geese that were down at the lake and they look forward to that
Being in the future again
I didn't think that they would succeed
Persuading the city of Los Angeles to let the water in again
Why did you think that they would not
How can you find the city of Los Angeles
So really this is a victory a great victory
David Gaines did not live to see the victory
He had died a year before in an automobile accident
Not far from Mono Lake
And so finally the the machine that Mulholland
Set in motion
Just kind of
Began to fall
Hit the
The whole
Picture of the Los Angeles Department of Water and Power and the city changed
The city negotiated
With Mono Lake
Folks and decided to give more water back to the lake
It gave up
On the idea of importing Klamath river water or Columbia River water
It
People's feeling
I bring more water in if it just encourages more growth that forces
Just to bring more water in you know
It's a sort of a
Or
It's the
Queen and Alice in Wonderland running faster and faster
And
Mentality
Has it sort of died and respectful death
You know if there's an occasional short
Well that's too bad
We're in the desert here
And we're not supposed to be
Like Miami
All the time every day of the year
To Infinity
After the damn failure my grandfather underwent
The most profound change that you can imagine and
But he had been a vigorous
Functioning 70-year-old man or 72-year-old man at the time of the
Faile
And he simply
Shrive
He come out to the ranch
She needs to sit in the living room with this cigar and
Conversation would go around and he would he would just shut his eyes he would sit there like some kind of
Sleeping GI
I was so
The child when I attend
The funeral
And his body
State and city hall
And
The Working Man
You came to pay their
Specs
And some of them cried
When I was 12 years old and that made a big impression on me cuz I had never seen
Grown man cry
And
I derived from that that this was the man who
Commanded a lot of love and respect in his day
And I've spent a lifetime trying to
Died that with all the
Facts that have been made on him by people who didn't know
Freeways are settling down believe it or not we check on the 405 and the 101
Leaving the Hollywood Hills
Not bad at all don't need to take
The Roots such as
Laurel Canyon Coldwater
Canyon or even Bowl
Drive
I'm Dr road map fly
For Captain Jorge
Ninja copter 7
Down to the last
Drop on orders from the interior Secretary of the United States
This was the first River on Earth to come under complete human control the only River in a thousand
Miles of desert so hot and dry
Today 30 million people depend on the Waters of the Colorado
This is the story
Of how that came to be
Las Vegas isn't supposed to be here no one dreamed there would ever be
Las Vegas on the Colorado River that in
Stark Baron Des
People would actually want to live
And develop a community and build a city in it people don't come to Las Vegas
Because
Carefully analyzed our
They come here because the economic potential is there we have the jobs
And we keep building Mega resorts on the strip
And we have a vibrant economy we pay no taxes
Gaming is footing the bill for us
Out of
Alligator
Community
Las Vegas is only one of a dozen cities feeding on the Colorado
Here it rains 3 in a year
About the same as in EG
Every week a thousand people move to Las Vegas
And each of them will use 350 gallons of cool clear water
Everyday
Why are you in the desert you shouldn't even be in the desert if you people would just send everybody away
You wouldn't have this problem
If you'd like
Like this kind of growth in your community
All these people
I'll have to go somewhere in this country
The Colorado River is the lifeblood of the Southwest
Without the Colorado without a stable water supply the Southwest would not look anything like it does
Without
Water
Without flowing water
All these desert places that we have
Settled and made populous
I really really unbearable
Environment
It All Began in 1857
When Joseph Christmas eyes ran a steamboat up to the desolate spot for Las Vegas now stands
Stopped by rapid
He said
The Colorado River shall be forever on visited and undisturbed
And turn back
But in 1869
John Wesley pow
Set off down the mysterious River
His was the last
Great scientific Expedition inside the United States
Entering the last
Part of the West
Unpenetrated by
The river Powell explored
Was
Well you have to give him Credit One Arm going down that River didn't do a thing about it
They had no idea where they'd find waterfalls
The kind of Rapid said run into and I remember
The first time I went down and I had to worry about whether that roar I heard in the distance
The waterfall 100 ft or just
Little
We now administer the Colorado and a great system of water works but in a few places
Power was a king's skeptical Observer
Determined to learn whether Americans could realistically settle the land along the Colorado
Bed by snow melt and rare violent storms
It was America's Sylvia's River
And one of the world's warmest
No River on Earth
The river was
Willful headstrong it would flow at
Flow of the Mississippi at low water
A little
Canyon really
I mean the Grand Canyon is huge but the actual
Riverbed
It's small
And this River would rise
70 f
It ran wild for 2 or 3 months every year and
It would get down to a trickle
In August
September
The fluctuations on the Colorado River is is amazing
It's just not a very predictable
River
It was an outlaw River and we couldn't let it not the regulated and that's why I think
I think it wasn't just that it was the only significant River in the southwest but that it was
So
This this nature that we say we love wild we really like it quite well regul
And we went after the
Colorado River with a kind
The special
How questioned whether the river could be controlled whether it could water the Arid West and weather it could be
Fairly divided Americans have bitterly debated the Colorado ever since
This year
All of whom lay some claim to its Waters
Who wants this River everyone wants this River everyone in the southwestern United States and
Northwestern Mexico as you flow down here it's hard to realize but this river is really cool
I'm Phoenix Tucson
Providing substantial amount of the water supply for Southern California Southern
Nevada provide substantial habitat for all kinds of Aquatic Life there's a lot of people
People competing for this River
When I was born
1912 there were no dams in the Colorado River it was a Wild River all from start to finish
Thought it was all right I think the rivers to run to the ocean
That was their idea it was probably a good one
There
There's a cry practically Nationwide to control the wild raging rampant Colorado River
Flooded The Yuma Valley in the all the irrigation land down there flooded every year without questioning it it was just
There needed to be some control structure on the Colorado to to stop those
Devastating annual floods
For all its Fury
Only a 30th the flow of the Mississippi
But it was the biggest river in a thousand miles of desert
In 1922
Herbert Hoover convened western states to divide the river's water
Half was claimed by the mountain states
For the rain and snow fell
And half by the desert States
For most of the farms in cities would be
So much
But the compact Reserve no water for Native Americans
And little for Mexico
Within a year
Bureau of Reclamation surveyors had located dozens of damn sites
The prime damn site was in a remote Canyon called GL
But the bureau on the fierce pressure from California congressman
Chose Instead The Narrows
Of Black Canyon
300 M
To the exploding population of Los Angeles
The first great dam would be here
A few miles from the Tiny Village of Las Vegas
Hoover Dam to me was a
I expected
Unbeliev
The man
Okay I could
It to start
No damn that size could be built
People didn't know how to do it
Who would pay for it it was
A huge leap into the realm of the unknown
No one had ever before stopped a river of this size
Hoover Dam would stop floods
Irrigate Farm
Generate low cost power for homes and factories
It would be bigger than the Great Pyramid of Egypt
Three times as tall as the Statue of Liberty
This was a depression like you never saw
And I felt very
That I could come to Boulder City
And go to work on Hoover Boulder Dam whichever one you prefer to call it works started here in 19
And the dam was dedicated on September 30th of 1935 by Franklin Roosevelt
Of course the first thing you have to do is get the river out of your way we made tunnels Through The Rock
I get it out of her way so we can get down to bedrock and then start the construction of
Damn and the river is not very anxious
To change this channel
Cuz you gradually squeeze it down you can throw the Taj Mahal in there and the river moves
Come down river
And what a thrill it was
That water gushed through those big diversion tun
And we went down
Through the desert to an Overlook and we could see it being constructed
My father had me up on his shoulders looking out cuz we were looking down over that in
Just terrifying but fascin
A million little ants running down there
They got $5 a
If they have just enough to wrestle a jackhammer up there 5
Were cleared out of that particular area where the shot
Not just to see these high schoolers work off of boats and chair attached to a rope
Some of those guys could spring around like monkey
And the basket that was being lowered down into the
Canyon
Oh I wanted to get on
Not so bad and right down it just looked like a barrel of fun
We just change shift
Kind of hard to swish swash of an arrow
Tumbling tumbling tumb
From way up there
And
Quite
I was stand
And I made a Mad Dash over to this guy
But along
Hard boiled superintend
He said to me
What are you going to do with all these blackity black truck
I said there's a man killed over here we'll get a moving this guy can't hurt anybody
Keeping those trucks moving
Was more important than anything
You know
We got to get this damn
I just bring that up
Is dial highball
This job was
It was on June 6th 1933
That's the first bucket of concrete
Was placed in the very lowest of the damn form
What a few months previously
Had blowed the unchallenged Colorado
The plan of the structure became app
Getting that concrete down into that
Canyon
120° heat and I just
Does that man was able to do a thing like
Degrees 140 in the tunnels
In the first month killed a worker every two days
San Francisco to New York City it had
Much much
Much more Concrete in it than the Empire State Building
I mean
Dozens of
Except for
Corridors inside it's an elevators it's absolutely solid
The best way from up here I've found to help everybody judge signs if you look at the vehicles driving back and forth across the top of it
So big and my father and mother said the water is coming in it's making electricity power that's what
I feel down in the dam I feel it the
What self is a powerful structure
How to look what it's holding back
Imagine what a reservoir the size of Lake Mead
Ways imagine the weight and all that weight wants to go down river it doesn't have
Have
Other
Passion
But to go
Downriver
And the only thing stopping it is
Thumb
700 ft thumb
Yes I stood on that Transformer deck and looked at that magnificent concrete structure
Couldn't help but
Thinking that tears something greater than the pyramids is greater than
Sphinx because it's not a monument to the Dead
This is a monument to the living
The damn is alive
And I know it gives
I had to stop and throw up the do
Wow look at that
Even a a damn hater
Astrid
I was tremendously impressed
By that damn
When I first laid eyes on it I felt like I had to get out of my car and kneel down in genuflect those engineers
I built something not just immense but really
Beautiful
53 million dollar bowl today I'm highest in the world is practically
All but a few of the remaining workers get their final paychecks from the stupendous day
And ahead of schedule and the depth of a great drought
And the Great Depression
Hoover Dam held
2 years of the Colorado's flow in a 100-mile reservoir so heavy it bent the Earth
Across creating its own tiny earthquakes
In the name of people of the United
Go home you bowled Adam
All right symbol of greater things in the future
And in the honored Pres
From many
I call you
Don't
Who was the greatest single source of electricity in the world
It's turbines with power the aircraft industry that help
To defeat Hitler
Would Light Up Downtown Los Angeles and a hundred other cities
It's water with irrigate thousands of funds in California
Hoover Dam proved it could be done it gave me the confidence to damn the
It also gave them confidence to plan dams for
Every single River in America
If anybody comes
In the
Several thousand years from outer space and they land there they will know exactly what happened
On this spot at that time just by reading the Stars
On the edge of Hoover Dam is a mosaic star map
It shows the alignment of planets and stars in the heavens on September 30th 1935
The day the dam was dedicated
It was designed to
Thousands of years
Anybody
Anas
More than anything else
Hoover convinced
We could conquer the Fatal dryness of the Great American Des
I didn't really appreciate
What this place was all about at 10:00 at night
I woke up in the morning
And I opened the blinds
And all I saw was Baron desert
And I thought I'd landed on the moon
Who live in Arizona say that they love the desert
From the perspective of the air conditioned home
If you talk to the frontier the pioneer
Is that wandered across it
Trying to get some place
Where they could live where they could sustain themselves
It was the most terrifying experience imaginable
Many people died
Crossing the great BAS
That immigrant Trail is
Littered with
Everybody thinks about the Donner
And how they died in the snow
But
People died
In the
When power first warned against oversettling the Arid West
Other scientists argued that
Rain would follow the pl
But plowing and planting would agitate the air
Cause clouds to form and Rain to fall
The frustration of trying to convince the Congress
That the
Just couldn't sustain
The level of population
Wanted to impose on the region
When they were trying to pound a square peg into a round hole
Pioneers went
The first thing that had to be done was to banish the idea that this was in any sense of Des
Please
Pioneers
Had no idea how dry it was out there they were going into a region that couldn't be farmed without irrig
And nobody
Was talking about irrigation
Throw corn or squash and melons a beans
I guess naturally we just learn how to use the water conservative list because we never had any water we live in
Eric Lynn you know we're just you don't irrigate any of that no no rain
The hopes have lived near the Colorado for a thousand years
On the heels of our Triumph at Hoover came a time in American history
Pray when we had the money and resolved to build on a grand scale
To subdue the rivers of the West
And to make them do our bidding
The original Mission of the beer Reclamation to reclaim the Arid West
Was was a calling that had some real Vision to it
In 1933 there was a stamp
Said conservation
Who is
End of the picture of a damn
So that was consolation then
So there is this great big rash to see how many dams we could build in this
No matter what the consequences would be later
The impact
That large store mainstream storage reservoirs had on salmon and other fishery resources
With something that was recogn
And then dismiss
That was the cost that was
Price that one paid for development
Finishing salmon for the vanishing Redmond winter food for the TR
Hydroelectric dams flood control dams irrigation dams in
Even plans to reroute the Colombia a thousand miles south
Into the Colorado
Before computers environmental impact studies or federal deficits
We built a thousand major dams over the next 30 years we
Virginia dryness out of existence
Grand Coulee and then we were building the five largest
Structures on
Simultane
All in one region of one country
Long Colombia roll alone
After Hoover return to the Columbia
Greatest Salmon River in the world
My 1955
55 dams on the Columbia and its tributaries
That
Engineers who worked on Hoover went up there
And looked at that can
And imagine this damn 4/5 of a mile wide
And 550 ft
They said it made Hoover look like nothing
Ethiopia on a whirlwind US tour he expresses the hope that such a damn might be
And almost no stretch of the Colombia was not a reservoir
There was unfinished business on the Colorado
The 19
Twenties that came down in here and actually did a full trip through the Grand Canyon and identify a whole series of dams that
Essentially would have backed up the Colorado River
In a series of stair step reservoirs all the way from the Mexico United States line all the way up into Wyoming
Coming in Colorado
The bureau began work on the dam in Glen Canyon
It would generate hydropower for Phoenix
And revenue to pay for other dams and would submerge 186 miles of Canyon
The Big Dam in the Colorado River
They went in the big capacity would be playing the Canyon Dam the 26 million acre foot capacity Reser
186 Mi long
That was the big one that was the money maker
It wasn't for irrigation it was just to make hydroelectric power
Grand Canyon was one of the most remote spots in America a hundred miles from the nearest
Paid Road
Hair Powell found the river smooth and
With Anasazi ruins on the banks
Barely 200 people had ever been through the canyon
The first year I ran down Glen Canyon was in 1954
And as we come near Lees Ferry probably 15 or so miles above Lees Ferry
There's marks on the wall there's something going on over there there's piles of dirt I looked up
We did
There are 600 or more feet above
You dot little guys wave on top of the rim
We look through the binoculars and
Damn this Canyon
Glen Canyon as it was
Glen Canyon as it will be at 11:30
I marveled
Because here was a sheer wall
Canyon
Muddy river running through it
And
I tried to visualize
Hoover Dam already in
That was what we were doing we were building a duplicate of Hoover
Stag
Me
To think of the job
But to be done
Reclamation Chief was the legendary Floyd Domini
Floyd domini is a household world in the 17 Western
The reclamation
Kennedy called me the nation's Waterboy
Senator Jackson at prevailed on Udall to suggest
Maybe it was time for me to
Retire
All I had to do was
Wish alert the White House
That these people
Twisted my tail
And pinching a little and
Just
Took care of it
He's sort of the the role model for a lot of of ways that the bureau approach things it was more of a
Turn the Torpedoes let's get this son of a b**** built
He got a lot of it built
I remember that the hydroelectric energy is the only
Pollution free energy
It's created it's renewable
You don't burn
Coal mine and you don't mind out of mind you don't drill out a well
You don't have 25,000 year half life full of rods from the atomic power
I think it's a shame that we haven't developed
Every single
Possible Kil
A lot from this renewable non-politan source of energy
Everyone in the in the great Reclamation including Western
Firmly believe that the Reclamation program was a must
For the girls and expansion of the West and we had no descend
Swim in the 40s and
Early 50s at least
The great moment
Damn Construction
Is when you finally realize that if you put the last bucket of concrete on the top of the dam and that
Now are prepared to
Close the tun
And let the River start
Making its way up
To the spillway levels
And and feel the lake
When Glen Canyon Dam was nearly complete
David Brower executive director of the Sierra Club
Visited The Condemned Canyons for the first time
Brower and the Sierra Club had stopped a dam on the Green River
In exchange for not objecting to the dam in Glen Canyon
Grand Canyon used to be filled with beaver
And no beaver in there anymore
A good fishing in there
It was just a
Quiet
No Rabb
To speak of
Has a very historic spots in there just
Nice place
Each one of them with a stream in it
Would you walk up this little stream then you turn left
And suddenly you're in one of the most remarkable designers
Huge Amphitheater
A much bigger than most of the casinos I've been in
Just a little slot of sky
A little bit of water coming over a waterfall
At the head of
Up to
A lot of
Smooth sandstone
If you touched it it just felt like velvet
And above that
Twisting funnel
Where the light came down
Kind of yellow
Then kind of dimmer and dimmer and then kind of Orange
An Exquisite place
Just about as beautiful as anything the Creator ever dreamed
Powell had been the first
First Outsider to see Glen Canyon
And these dozens of side Canyons
Brower
Would be one of the last
And a Grand Canyon this was a crit
Pickle Time
And I recall the decision I had to make
Whether we could close the
That year or have to wait another year
I've seen again and I'd seen the side again as my family had seen in my new but a beautiful place it was
I testified in
Lack of comprehensive thinking that is going under the entire project and came up with
Very strong Arguments for stopping the entire project
I wanted at least at the last moment
To appeal to Steward you doll
And I wanted to get in to talk to him because that was the last day they were going to close the
And start feeling Glen Canyon and I got to his office but never got to see him because he
He had this other agenda
Of course all the upper
States people and politicians were saying close the gates
And all the downstream people who relied on the water coming on through
Don't close
Hi I didn't have this last desperate hope
And we could
They the closing of the day on the closing of the river valves
Stop any further filling
Until we thought a little bit harder about the alternatives
And that January
I fail
So Ben Canyon started filling
We finally got an estim
That indicated and that we would get up to power plant intake levels
By the end of July
And so I made the recommend
That we closed the
And
But I was the one person it was the skin position
And there's where my big failure was
We had the AR
We had the votes
And for reasons that I still do not understand I didn't do what I should have done
I
And I didn't act
Shut it down into the
Canyon landscape I can see from afar
It's plugging the river
The place where Glen Canyon Dam stand
As I look around at this incredibly beautiful and creative work
Of writing on the wall
A kind that says
Probably and beautifully
Man was here
We're looking down $583 ft or 175 m
Goodbye hat
The reservoir was christened 100 years to the day after power passed through Glen Canyon
Glen Canyon Dam was built to generate hydropower for homes industry and air conditioning
In Phoenix
And to power pumps which lift the Colorado 300 miles uphill
To new farms and towns in Arizona
Today
4 million people a year visit Glen Canyon Dam and its Lake
But I felt from the very start
Should be like Paul because
Paul is the man who had made the canyon famous
He was the man who was treated the father of the Bureau of Reclamation he was the one who made the reports to Congress that indicated
Addicted the West could never be developed by private Enterprise alone and it would take
The power and muscle of the federal government to develop and settle the
Properly
So I thought Lake Powell was the proper name for that res
One of the most outrageous things that ever happened
Question name the reservoir the Flatwater
Behind Glen Canyon Dam after John Wesley Powell
Reservoir that flooded some things that he thought were the most beautifully he had ever seen
I'm sure
If you're around
He would be after the person who thought of that idea and you say you can't do that
Maybe Dominique's Flatwater or something
Lake pow
When you damn a river you always lose
You
Prov
Something for somebody else
And I have somebody in the middle get upset
Extended a Goldwater had been a strong advocate for Glen Canyon Dam
Prayer soon I guess probably one of the most beautiful reservoirs in the world
And as you write on it you can see things you could not have seen in the river
But I just assume I never see them
Left Bank
And I wound around I came across
A very narrow place
I could just barely get my boat through and I looked back
Down and the Sun at that particular moment
Had come down just like a beam right
Back down into the water
And what it showed me
Spirals that I had looked up at
They're 2000 Anasazi
Buried in the water now
But they decided to practice Advantage was without way that this was a controversial damn it kicked off the environment
Mentalist movement in the United States
Because a handful of people had taken the trouble to find out what an Exquisite little canyon this was
These Canyons now lie 600 ft below the surface of Lake Powell
But I have to be honest with you I've been happier
If we didn't have the lake
Piece of water
If you had to vote
Today
On damn in Glen Canyon would you vote against it
Cuz I
I've become convinced
Well water is important
Particular those of us who live in the desert
It's not all that important
8 million years of geolog
To change came to a sudden end
Environmental hav
Swiftly took hold Downstream
For years the Colorado had run 85° and Rich with silk
It runs freezing cold and Crystal Clear
Most of the Native fish
Which had evolved over a million years in the warm salty water
Into Extinction
Lake Powell evaporates 10 ft a year
The Violet natural floods which redistributed River Sands were replaced by
Govern not by the rain
Goodbye
Power demand in Phoenix
Would you believe a fish story in which a transport plane is
I had no sympathy for those who felt that nature couldn't
No I ad
The picture can improve upon man we're probably
Supreme Being but
In the realm of river
I think
Man can improve up
We're not trying to recreate what was here before the dam that's kind of I mean it's almost impossible to do but
Still trying to protect the endangered species 40 years ago there were no studies of the environmental change Glen Canyon Dam
Set in motion
National Environmental laws did not exist
Now
A bureau team studies those changes in the river
System
Towels men found the ancient river half a mile wide at its mouth
Pouring into the ocean
By 1967
Hoover
Glen Canyon
And eight of the damn stop the river in a chain of giant reservoirs
Accepting very wet years
The Colorado River no longer reaches the sea the remains of the river vanished into the sand
In Northern Neck many many people have had lives and livelihoods
Cities have been built and huge amounts of food produced that just would never have happened without
About these Reclamation projects and I don't think anyone can truly logically sit down and say in the grand scope
Of everything in context that that was an evil thing to do
We believe that this is where we emerg
Cuz this is what we call
The center of the
Grand Canyon
Is one of the most sacred
Place
In the universe as far as I hope he's as concerned
Very important
Plus we don't want to destroy this
I know somebody mentioned it yesterday you're trying to play
Well I don't know
I don't think we are able to do that
Because we're human who are moral be
I know some of you are very very bright
Smart
You know
I don't think you can go beyond
On behalf of air star helicopters at myself
Like the
Grand
Avenue of all the Lady Gaga
The Colorado River flows down the canyon
They come together right in front of us at a place called
Confer
To the Hopi
The Confluence of the Colorado and the little Colorado
Marks the place where humans first emerged from the earth 8 years ago
Antenna I guess 9 million years old
You take a ballpoint pen and just draw a
Just a piece of paper that's the game out of Eros
The truck every year for 9 million years
To make the grand can
On the very day Glen Canyon began to fill
The Bureau announced plans for more power dams on the Colorado
Including one and Marvel can
Not far from the confluence
Was a wonderful damn
Sure Canyon walls over
Straight up and down it's just near perpendicular as you could get
And a very Nar
So it was a
Perfect damn
Come over Gorge is a remarkable
In Colorado
French and trenches
Very deep in their very steep wall
There are places where the
The river is polished that marble
Glor
Are you have internet and are well into the red wall
Stone formation
Place they finally decided to build
The so-called marble dance
And they had a big operation there the regular Community was
Performed in the vicinity
They had a
An aerial Tramway that came down from the Canyon Rim they had to test the Rock
In order to do that they
So they began testing the cliffs there they Rock for its strengths
These new dams would flood 140 miles of Canyon between Hoover and Glen
They were the centerpiece of an immense plan to generate more power for growing cities
Having
Glen Canyon
And realizing how great a loss that was for all time
Hey I've just had a new determination with let's not do it
Anymore
And certainly not the grand
So we began to do what we could do to block the ATT
Cuz if you're a Reclamation to build a two Grand Canyon Dam
Now a big smile
The Grand Canyon is so deep that tourists on the rim cannot see the river
Broward testified before Congress
At the dams would be wasteful
An impractical
This is big questionable wouldn't you compromise wouldn't you take just a little teeny weenie down the Grand Canyon
And I said no the Grand Canyon wasn't lying to trade
Permanent
Mass
It would have altered it forever
So we had to stop
And it wasn't easy
They didn't want any dams build any place on the Colorado River
It's not hard for me to understand that
Of Arizona voters
I don't like to
To see these dams built I wish there were some way we didn't have to
Have to build them
But speaking for people who are mounting by the mill
And I expect to live to see the day when my city will be the 5th or sixth Lar
Just in America
I have to argue for these people
Commissioner domini pointed out that reservoirs would not be seen from any Vista point on the Canyon Rim
And that Marble Canyon filled with water
Would be more accessible to tourists and Power
Should we flood the Sistine Chapel so tourist
Can get closer to the ceiling
How you know that was in response
To the
Members of Congress from Arizona on all who said
We will make a beautiful Lake there so people can see the scenery better
So we ran ads in the New York Times the chronicle
Did Los Angeles Times Sacramento baby
Fan ads all over the Washington Post
Where we thought it would work
Americans
Tired
Have the idea that dams were conservation
The engineers argument that you can't place this water you can't let it flow to the Sea unus
Began to pay
I'm on the public so it was not that hard to say well
Consider that we have enough damage for an island to see if we can't keep some Rivers alive
The dams would rise like bookings on either side of Grand Canyon National Park
Technically outside the park boundary
But Brower argued they would still
The Grand Canyon
I resent the fact that Dave Broward deliberately
I slept the public
About Bridge Canyon Dam
Play Domin
Are you still this day figured that the all I did was telling truth about what was going to happen to the Grand Canyon and
He gave the impression deliver
That we were
Flood the Grand Canyon National Park
There was actual tourist
Where would the lake be in this View
We use the Bureau of reclamations photograph
Of how
Would be inundated
It was an absolute lie and then brought knew it
So that sanctimonious bastard did he deliberately
We talked about damning the
Canyon
That changed everything
The Grand Canyon
The reader's dig
Said it was a bad idea
My Weekly Reader
And
The Beast was out of the bottle
I have no AP
I was
A crusader
For the development of
I was the mess
I was the
It went out and and argued persu
After develop our rivers and and water
Supplies for the benefit of people
I don't apologize
As public opinion swelled
Commissioner domini held out for at least one damn
We came very close to building that
Site was
The general feasibility studies were prepared
That damn was nearly a reality
I think the story goes
Once the Floyd domini went overseas on
An inspection and it wasn't until he left the country that
Are people that immediately hot old and and came to agreement not to include those struct
Pictures in the in the final legislation
The
We're taken out
Of the authorization bill
He had to be gone
For that to
Was such a historic moment nobody knew it
The time but that really
It was the beginning and it was a big beginning
Of the end of the age of Dance
We just come into what's called The Marble Canyon Dam Site Area
And in the
Late '50s early '60s this area was actually proposed
For a damn
And this was one of the damn sites that was
Was being explored
There's added tunnels on both river right and River left and that's primarily where you see the mine tailings
On River Ridge you can see a couple of Bureau Reclamation graffiti signs
The one that's straight across from us is
The middle of the dam was to be located
A living river is a very exciting thing I should remain an exciting thing
Rivers done a very good job in the Grand Canyon has made a beautiful Canyon
And I'm not ready to penalize the river please a couple
Hydroelectric Engineers ever
Brower had one
Glen Canyon was the last Damn built on the Colorado
But saving Marble Canyon did not stop the flood of people drawn to new homes and new
Jobs in Arizona
In 1969
Lyndon Johnson authorized
The central Arizona project
For the millions of Americans west of the Continental Divide
It'll provide more water for growing cities
It'll provide more water for expanding Industries for the farmers crop
And for the ranchers cat
And let us build
And Power
Kind of network of projects for irrigation
For electricity and finally for recreation
So by taking this action today
That we are making the Waters of the West
A little sweeter and we'll make the grass
This is the most expensive Water Works in Bureau history
The lifeline without which
Farms and homes in central Arizona could not exist
Glen Canyon power
And a giant coal-fired power plant
Drive pumps which lift the Colorado 300 miles
Uphill into
Tucson and Scottsdale
Phoenix has grown so large
That
Rome and Manhattan together
Could all fit within its city limits
This is our Cambria 2 model
Is the largest home that we do in this particular Community it's about 1600 ft
The next room I want to show you is our third bedroom or Den
Right now I want to let you know that Arizona
Is about
Second hottest real estate market in the country next to Atlanta
Well the only thing they can get out of balance is if we get too many people
As I say when I was born here they were about 10,000 people living in the whole valley
Now they're 2 million
2 million is
Large number of people for us to service with water
The things that Reclamation deal in building water projects
Allowed a lot of growth
But the problem we face today is that
There's just not enough water to go around
We have underground watering systems with a small drain
To every plan small drip
We also have sprayer systems for the grassy areas and of course this is called Desert Landscaping
And my grandmother would go over there and fetch water
Very little
And
Expected last maybe for a couple of days
And then when I when I see my grandmother
I wash dishes after dinner she put a water into one
Put her hand like that and she put
That same water into another
And then then she finally
Throw it out and that's how she uses water
Because of water has to last a long time
The reason why I would live in this desolate area is because
Is
And that's the only way that you can be as
To the spiritual being
And the closer you are to the spiritual being
The more that you are will maintain your humbl
So we look at this survival in terms of
Maybe thousands of years in the future
As you can see right now we're lucky
The Fountains going off
Right through the trees over here
That goes off every hour on the hour
The fountain
Shoots up over 500 ft it's actually taller than the Washington Monument
There will never be enough
Water
In the Colorado River
To satisfy all the man on ever we will never augmented by relocating Another River from the
Northwest to make it bigger and when the pie doesn't grow
You just cut smaller pieces of
Perhaps we've created
Some problems that we'll never solve and by attract
People making it easier for people
To move into a harsh environment
I don't know why everybody should have a
Cool Maryland backyard
I don't know why they should have a green lawn and when
Practice would look better in the desert envir
I can sit here in 1995 and I can say to John Wesley pound you were wrong
The Colorado River at that time was a whole different river system
And it was running wild
And it didn't look very manageable
But we've engineered our way out of that problem
We have
So many dams and Reservoir
Net system that there is adequate water
Colorado
But the system is fragile
Runoff predictions went to Ryan 1983 thundering water ripped Boulders in Pulver
Whenever a little fancy I don't want the damn to go all at
It would stick out Hoover Park and Davis Downstream because they're not
To handle 26 minutes computer water coming down all at once
If Hoover Dam collapse the entire economy of the Southwest would be
Catast
Affected
We we can't imagine until something like this happens how dependently become and the Liberties we've taken
With the natural order
In Phoenix
The average August temperature is over 100
Here and there amidst the abundance are a few abandoned orange groves in subdivisions
Their supply of Colorado water shut off
This is what happens when the water stops
Today
More people farms and industries depend on the Colorado
But on any comparable river in the world
Never had such a river been asked to do so much
When you drive
Interstate 5 between San Francisco and Los Angeles UC
Feels smiles and miles of cuddersfield so you see row crops and sea Orchards anything out there's some
It's a real
This just would have been possible within the pre-existing natural order the
Is coming from hundreds of miles away
To concrete River
Without these fasting Water Works that we know which are all but invisible
Somewhere off in the distance is a huge
Without carrying water
But if
Somehow the water
Everybody is conscious of water
If you had for the river with a buck and empty bucket you'll ever get shot
Water makes
Can
A low value piece of property into something you can grow let
Wanted they would just be a dry desert here really
Water brings the green out here it's it's man-made compared to
What are you doing it back east
This looks like garlic over here there's a young almond Orchard over here right now we've got a field
Share this ready for planning for something probably gotten their Tomatoes these are pistachio trees here
More lettuce over here and garlic over here see this Bronco right here this tough grass you see on the edge of the road
This is the way it would have
100 years ago before water
10,000 trucks a day whole food to Market on Interstate 5
Hundreds of miles through the heart of California for nearly a cent
Congressman Governor's presidents and Farmers have fought bitterly to make nature do their bidding
They have
The history of the world here it is
Drier than North Africa and to bring water to this dry land we built the world's largest
And most expensive water works
This is the most completely transformed landscape of its size anywhere on Earth
Food
How did we achieve this and why do generations of Americans fight over this land where
Sierra Nevada rivers to the east have flooded a few weeks each spring since the beginning of
And fed the great swamps
100 mile
Every summer
The marshes evaporated
The Valley shimmered in withering Heat
It was the American Serengeti
This whole area was known as the Huron sink
It was kind of a swampy type thing with water
Un
I'm not very deep
But moving in and out
That's where the Indian
And
Do some fishing
Hard to believe today
The onions they were there during the winter month
And then they had high tailored over where it was cooler in the summer over for the Sierras
The Valley's natural Web of Life
Had evolved over thousands of wet Winters and dry summers in a few game Reserves
Bits of the original Valley survive to this day
Unbelievable
80 to 100 million bucks and geese with winter
The sky was black
I've heard it from people still alive
This guy was black
There were Grizz
All over
And there were antelope
Millionaire tullioch
You can find here and there tiny tiny little
But
It was
It's completely and irre
And UT
Play transformed now
The Central Valley has one
Drawback
It stops raining in most years in April or May and it starts raining again
In November
And then when it
The town of Sonora got 78 in of rain
6 weeks
Central Valley was a lake
The size of Lake ontar
It was 250 miles long and 40 miles wide and
Underwater
The only way to get
San Francisco to Sacramento was by boat
Sacramento was completely
Play underwater in 1850 and again in 18
From the moment
That flood receded the politician
The state legislatur
Said we've simply got
To do something
The control nature here
Or we can't continue to live here
And that was really the beginning
One of the not transformation of the valley
A 19th century law allowed anyone to claim land over which he could sail in a boat
Henry Miller staked out his claims for
Section of land in a boat
He was just another one of those
California who came here from somewhere else reinvented him
Completely he did a
He would float around and Mark Drive posting around and marked his territory and the law
Required to be done from a boat so that's just what he did and then when the flood went away
According to history he put a boat in a Buckboard wagon and then had it pulled by a team of horses
A buggy or wag
And what traits in across
A considerable
Whose Empire
Ultimately
1 million
90,000 Acres
For his era
You'd have to take your hat
And he was the first person to build a
Yes significantly size damn in California
And that led to
1200 other
Significant size that we built since then
In the late 19th century
Pioneers built small dams
Drained marshes and dog canal
They found themselves at the mercy of Nature and the heavens for rain
They hope that the range would be timely enough to to get a
Obviously it was
And if they got into a reasonably West
They could do reasonably well
It's a lot of praying
Said that with a lot of
Yeah they sent their wives
The church I know every Sunday
But a vast aquifer of pure water lay just Underground
Built up
Like water in a sponge
Over thousands of winters
In a few places it even gushed up to the surface
After World War I
Traveling salesman went from Farm to farm selling powerful new turbine pumps
Now farmers could pump as much groundwater as they needed
In 1929
California pulled ahead of Iowa as America's leading Farm state
Even as Dr
Settled over the valley
Before long rose had pumped the San Joaquin water table down
And by 1930
They had $24,000 turbine pumps on the aquifer
Drawing it down to 100 ft below the surface
Deep rooted Oaks on the San Joaquin Plains began to die
70,000 refugees from the
Football present a new problem to California
Water
Bring up and living conditions alarm the health author
These newcomers seek to make a living by following the har
Working in the fields called for more labor
The Promised Land
To California
They're almost all
People driven from their own homes by dust storms without ill
Hard
Some of the most famous
Photograph
Ever taken hard Dorothy Alliance photographs of the Okies if you will the migrants in the Great
What people may not know is that most of those photograph
Thanks for taking into San Joaquin Valley
California
Where it
That's where the
Population
Migration
Waves of
Refugees found Farmers leveling new tracks of land
Cheap labor and cheap water were key to the expansion
But migrants could not see
Was that girl is we're pumping the aquifer dry
I think about hundreds of gallons a minute
Sounds like a firehouse there was something like 24,000 pumps big pump
Here
They overdraft
They mind it
So fast
That the valley subsided
Portions of the San Joaquin Valley dropped three
You're pulling out a hundred buckets of water
And only a couple is being replenish
If this is a this is a losing deal
There's no question about it
By the middle of the Great Depression
The promised land California's Great Central Valley was running out of water
Now
Farmers could even limit their pumping and produce less or they could search for new water
At the Sierras in if there is a cloud layer or a cloud formation you can see through the heights you can see the snow
Just capping the whole top of the
The whole top of the mountains that surround the valley floor
Northern California's West blizzard raging for a week without a letter buries the CL in the Bible region in 13 ft
Every Spring Ciara snow melt roared down the salmon rivers and out to sea
Cut off from the outside world by snow choke highways
Evans
Just to the east of the farm counties once got 73 ft of snow deepest ever recorded
Anywhere in the world
Scores of cars only the federal government which had just conquered the Colorado River could move the snow
The Farms across California
The New Deal
Came along
An exquisitely opportune time
It was
Growers turn to Franklin Roosevelt
America's newest engineering wonder is about to be dedicated
By the president of the United States
I have the right
Congratul
We'll have builded the bulldog
Even greater than Boulder Dam
The Central Valley Project
Here we have the most elabor
Irrigation
Project public work
Project ever built
What is desperately needed
Many politicians believe that the time that the government ought to be doing
This kind of stuff but he did
Reservoirs
Order an area the size of Lake Michigan no one had ever built anything like
Complex than Hoover Dam
It will be the biggest Public Works project since the Great Wall of China
It would be the most expensive Water Works in history
Monument
On behalf of the Bureau of Reclamation I like to welcome all of you to
That's the damn my name is Sherry and I'm a beer tour guide today
Shasta dam is the second largest concrete gravity type dam in the United States now this was
Instructor during the end of the depression that's gave him was 5,000 people in their families employment this was a big deal
And people did come from everywhere to get a job
Right now in 1935 most Americans had never heard of the
Fiorella of reclamation
This obscure agency would remake the face of the continent
These giant irrig
Act of 1902
Congress had passed the ACT a quarter Century before
To stop the sort of land grabs Henry Miller had
Frustrated
Go to the headquarters of the Bureau of Reclamation in Washington
You see murals all over the place and they
I picked
Grand development
And
Cultivation of land
And the arrival of settlers
New land new land all through irrigation otherwise it wouldn't exist
Those murals are everywhere
And of course
You're not in the west very long before you realize that the key is water
I think clearly that the original intent was if we got the water
To the land
We can put Farmers on it
This was a settling of the West
That was the best of intense and in fact it was written into the
This was going to be
12 hours this was going to be for people
Who formed $160
Days after Congress passed the Reclamation Act in 1902
Speculators real estate brokers and Congressman began their horse Trading
Everyone could see that land with water was worth more than land without water
And every Senator wanted a water project
By law
Water would be sold at a fraction of its cost
It's too small 160 Acre Farms
It was true that many small farms would soon get government water
But eventually
The largest recipient of the largest water project in history
Would not be a small farmer
But the Southern Pacific Railroad
Largest landowner in California
By World War II CVP canals would work their Way South
And soon transform the valley into the Bread Basket of the world
Far to the South
Farmers around Tulare Lake begin lobbying for their own water project
But high water
Could be
45 Mi about 22 Mi down that way in about 22 miles up this way and then it'd be about 10 miles
And 10 miles this way 10 miles west 10 miles east
And then
You'd be about 22
Feet deep
If it was the Deep
This part of the lake that was by the water which
Sound is on there
And then your face should be Swimming by
Tulare Lake was 2 million years old
One of the oldest Lakes on Earth
45 miles long it was the largest freshwater lake west of the Mississippi
When it flourish
In May and June with the
The whole celebrity
So it could be twice three times the size of Lake Tahoe and what years
It was probably the last place in the Central Valley that really was
If you get a lot of rain we had a lot of Lake
We didn't get much rain we had very little late and that's why a lot of people said it's kind of
Magical
You know a lot of rabbits and coyotes and things like that
So it was a it was just a real nice spot you know for hunting and fishing
4 years North American Fleet has been produced most profitably on large farm
But today none is more thoroughly industrialized in the 50,000 acre to Laura Lake Ranch
Not far from the lake on land once claimed by Henry Miller
Some of the wealthiest farmers in the world raised wheat and cotton
We have about 35
Bob's
Pictures of grain and
7,500 AC
Cot
We have 250 MI
Canals and ditches
On our Ranch
All of our land is
Under irrigation
And dryers
Growers could Farm bits of the lake bottom
But they wanted to farm it all in 1940 the bureau agreed to build irrig
Vacation dance on Rivers feeding the ancient Lake the law would then Force Growers to sell off their huge
The idea of
Subduing nature
Captiv
At the hall country
Practically
Are the Army Corps of Engineers Civil Works branch of the Army and the purification
Cannot appropriate enough money
That's enough for these agencies to build more dams
I'll give you your dad you give me mine that's the way it works
Here's to Federal
She's going to two different committees
For author
Two different sets of rules
All
From the same pocket
Federal Tre
And the core and the bureau ended up in
Better better r
Over who could get
To the next damn side first
The Corps of Engineers had far different
Legislative auth
They could build a project without acreage limitation
They could build your project
With no operation maintenance responsibility for the
For the beneficiaries of the project
And no repayment
Responsib
From the benef
So this was pretty tough compet
The core damn the rivers
Dried out the leg
And then brought back what had been to Larry's water to irrigate the dry lake bed
Many hundred
Became these diet
Business
These corporations have so much we
Practically free they basically have run AG
Thousands of Acres of cotton in
Thousands really I'd say probably
Million Acres
I didn't know in this area all around us from
Right back to Texas as far as you can see is cotton
So you know it's big acreage
Overwhelms people who come into the area and look around but
But the water is the essential thing without that water
Can't grow the cotton
I
Donatellite Basin just a couple years ago and
Find a lake I know I was
Approaching it
I was suddenly on it
And then I was miles into it
In my car
Completely obliterated
Blade is now 50 miles of cloud cotton field along Interstate 5
This is just like Las Vegas
Never stops in my father's front room talking about
Plowing the land 24 hours a day keeping it
Preparing the soil for planting and how they would swing in quarter-mile
You know it was about Lady of these of linking huge tract
Plot the land to level the land turn the land to to irrigate
We had built the CVP to relieve strain on over pumped groundwater
But with so many acres of new crops Farmers increase their pumping
The aquifer
And now the exploding population of Los Angeles want Valley Water
Even with the Central Valley Project
California's once again wanted
More
Does Papa Brown
This past promise California
But they would have
Of water
Growers ask Governor Brown to build a state financed flood control and irrigation project
Oh my father seem to be
Obsessed
With water
He talked about it
All the time in fact I remember when he would give speeches
Running for governor
The last time
He would give these speeches and talk about water all the time and he'd come back and he said I know it's not sex
I know people aren't listening
But water is important
Made it happen
A man-made River 600 miles long
It's always a disaster
Whether it's a Dr
For a flood
That gets the state rolling again and in 19
One of the worst
What
Went over his bags in the Yuba City and
Down in the Sacramento Valley is almost
Destroyed
Pat Brown n
That almost all Californians believed
Flood control and IR
He wanted to build
Statewide
It was an unheard of idea
For any state even the rich State like California
To build something
That big
Brown State Water Project squeaked by on a 3% margin
Even though we already had the largest Water Works in the world
The theory was it if any water
The ocean it was wasted
And so you got to grab
And put it somewhere else
Large scale excavation project
Such as harbors and canals
The University of California and the atomic energy Commission
Tested nuclear explosions for Excavating waterways
Sedan was detonated at 10:00 a.m. July 6th 1962
3 seconds
Disaster
Officials abandoned any thought of nuclear Canal building in the Central Valley
On its own
The state of California was building its own water works just as big just as expensive as the Central Valley
Play project
Background Waterworks would cost as much as the Manhattan Project
The size of the state Water Project is something you almost have to see but believe horrible
Solita
And almost half a mile
Talk about 150 ft high of the Eiffel Tower
The pump
If it had to be mountains is about 3,000 ft so you have a river running uphill
Returns of a mile even before the Central Valley Project was finished we
We were already building a
Project just as big
The presidential helicopter stairs up clouds of dust as
Federal state conservation endeavor
I'll blow up this Valley
By the late '60s
Federal and state water works had lifted the rivers out of their ancient beds
And deliver them to every corner of the great dry Valley
Soon
Bureau of water would reach even the Westlands most desolate part of the San Joaquin
1000 square mile District as dry as the Mojave
The local Congressman predicted that the Westlands would soon be settled by thousands of small farmers
Need more
It's okay
A large bumps are going to a 283 decrease the total release of feather river
From 4,000 to 3,500
You really have to go to the control room
State and federal water
In Sacramento
I mean here we had these Rivers
Big
You have
A few techn
Sitting at a big
Computers
And I Reg
The whole thing
I thought every morning they decide
He's going to get how much water and power and they just meter it out and steady flow to 32 million people and 10 million AC
Feet
My 1974
The state of California had the sixth largest economy in the world
Larger than all but the five greatest industrial n
Without Rain
Farmers could grow nearly all the fruits and vegetables of the Midwest and Florida
Going to Canal
The farm really real big here
So
But I really miss
Make sure the
Coy
Everything I left
Then the machine came
And we all got scared as if we're going to be out of a job
But no
Who would drive the machine it was easier
If it rained in the summer we'd be in
Trouble it's the fact that through irrigation we can
Feistley
By the water at the right time
You can stress
The cotton plant you cannot give it water for a while
Not plant thinks it's going into a drought and it's going to put on the balls then you put the water to it
Can you get a better crop
Rain is an enemy
So we're
Ask with that dry summer and combine irrigation and you got you got something
Magical
The new water supplies brought new mechanization and spectacular production that continues
The University of California joined with Growers and manufacturers
For you you're talking about Farms that $20,000 Acres
50,000 Acres 100,000 acres and these lands just overwhelm anything
The people thought about
Eastern United States
There was just nothing like
Talk about it everybody else in the country was relying on God
And these guys got
Get out from the US government
They got it
When they wanted
Time of day
Day of the month
Time of the year
And
And they got
I almost
Free a few researchers noted alarming changes amid the prosperity
Accumulation of salt and pesticide residue
Worsening conditions for Farm labor
The lack of small farms
And The Disappearance of salmon
Congress did not share their concerns and Western water projects
Roll through Congress as they had for decades
I've always referred to it as the iron triangle which is really an all
It was developed between local sponsors
Their Congressional
On delegation
And the Bureau of Reclamation or the water development agency the Corps of Engineers
They were the heart
And the soul
They were the the oil that made the engine of the Congress run
People voted for each other's day
Every Congressman wanted one
And every Congressman got one if he voted for everybody else
The way that
Translation
Often was
The committee Chairman's favorite damn was stuck onto it even though it was an education
Damn
Mean
I mean the Civil Rights
For example would have never been
Without the benefit of
Of using you know
Pork barrel of water project
Staff in the White House
And
Bud
Prepared as a matter of routine a list of water
Which were not justified and not not
Be funded
President Nixon and then President Ford to all of course said in those very interest
Christina and I really appreciate
The hard work you've
Want you to prepare this list but
No way am I going to do this and they reject
Politicians they knew how
The Congress operated in and President Carter was an outsid
Hi Jimmy Carter do sell them to swear when presidents come in and think that their
This is a serious
Steak they're only
One element of government
So Along Comes This
For repeated farmer and Governor ninja Carter who looks
Barely a month in office
Carter cut funds from 19 Western water projects under construction
Saying they were bad for the environment
I'm too expensive
Ladies and gentlemen
I give you the
Listen to the United States
President cart
They're
Night
In his office
Listen there were 12 advisors with him
You know all 12
So don't do this
And he voted he voted yes they all voted no and he went ahead and did it
No President Carter
There was a chip on his shoulder and a hit
Nice pocket
That he was going to stop a lot of
Project
Unnecessary it was the first time that any politician had taken a 2x4 and
Count the you know the donkey on top of the head
You're dealing here with projects in the
Central Arizona that go back
30 or 40 years
Thousands of hours
Of hear
Why why was
The decision
Let's take the money out of the budget why couldn't we announce that a review process was underway
It was
Like
It it struck the institution there were immediately
Meetings
Odd
How would the westerners
Wow the president
I would hope that we don't get to that point where there is a showdown at noon not
The Western
Either president been badly misinformed or his action demonstrates a callous disregard
For the welfare of the people of the states affected
Mastig
The Secretary of
This list
President
Sticking his nose and something that he didn't understand and didn't know
Didn't appreciate
That environmental concerns will not be the only thing
Which will be
Cranked into your investig
I mean clearly present Carter was right
These projects
When you looked at
We're completely
I complete waste of the taxpayers money
At one point I said
Yeah Mr secretary
I'm not sure this list is all bad
I think there's some projects here that that don't
And it was
Katana Brooks
Some of them are $168 million over authorized cost $192 million over
53 million 11 million 10 million
I think the review is Justified
People pulled your side in the hallway
You can't
You can't do this
We've got to stick together
We've got to hold together
This is an assault on all of
If they get my Water Project they're going to get your
I'm going to help
Your water project
This project
Need to be
I looked at very close to I personally don't believe in any of the projects ought to be built
But I'll keep an open mind
And it was the Bell that could not
Be on wrong
And it it sent out
A message
To other members of Congress
Who weren't from the West
That here was something
It was a mess
Here was a place if you wanted to go with it the waste of taxpayers money you could if you wanted to build your Environmental
You
For the present
For what he did
But he Chang
Again the entire
Political
Of all these dollars
Spent Water Project
Our symbol
There their symbols of
Of
That they're always something much larger
Larger than what they really are
In the end Carter could not stop
Nothing would ever be the same
He sent investigators to see what large-scale irrigation had achieved in the Westlands largest water district
In America
The Reclamation project that
To begin with
Visual
Family Farm
Of a sub
Nature
They didn't visualize Farms that were going to make enough money to send the
Used to college
You're even send them to attend
They visualize the farm that
Grow
And maybe a little Surplus say goodbye a bag
Salt
Those have
Dad had lived out here for many years
Had seen what happened to the homesteaders where they dried up and gone away it's 160 Acres was not
Was too small to be a viable
It was
Who's going to get the benefits of this Federal investment
Is it going to be rich guys
Going to be speculators
No we don't want that to happen we want it to be Farmers Family farmers
We end up in California
Where were irrigating
Do you even go back to
50 60,000 acres in a single holding
So is far different
What was visualized but 160th and limited in the 192 Act
There was not a single $160 Acre Farm in the Westlands Growers
In the government had been arguing since the beginning
Over when this thousand square miles would be broken into small farms
Now and owning 168 Acres
My wife could have 160 the husband can have 160 in it had 20 kids and if you had
An app Susie somewhere and you had
Been over here and there
You can see what began to happen
And we found ways to comply that
That we could make the econom
Next work and if it
You know creating some subsidiary organizations if it meant
Having your son have a 160 acres and you have 16 acre
You did that cuz that's what I took to survive it was
You know there was no big no kind of scheme to
Rip
The treasure is
No way to make things work
Local chamber of
It was together with the local Cattlemen's Association and the cotton growers association and we all
Who arrived at agreement
That you should spend the federal money to bring us the water
Hundreds of mill
Of dollars
Federal
And we bestowed it on a very
Small number of people
And we
With a prom
That they would break up their Farms
That they would
Provide rural communities throughout
And the large farm
I and their lawyers have the ability to to morph themselves into
Any size form that you wanted to make
Not only growing subsidized crops
But then they were receiving subsidized water to grow that subsidized crop
And the federal treasury was paying farmers in other parts of the country not to grow that crop these people had
Hundreds of ways
Skin the cat
They had predicted that there would be perhaps a 30 or 40% increase in agricultural productivity
And in fact over the first 10 years it had increased by 300%
Can we get that harvested the 7 days a week
16 hours a day
I work from 6:00 to
And then when the barley came 18 hours a day
We didn't know
Adele
The the first
The time that I went down to
Huron was the largest
Community that had lost its doctor didn't have a high school and didn't have a newspaper
There was one grocery store there were I think four bars of course everyone was living in very
Dilapidated rental housing the actual conditions
So we discovered the people were living under there
We're as bad or worse than the worst conditions that I've encountered in Africa South
The Sahara or Southern India or any parts of Latin America
The water out here it's always been a
And I say mister because
Without the water I mean you would would be in a desert sand right now
I mean that's what
The big corporate farmers who they are today but the fact that you know there is water out here in
Create jobs creates homes creates a wealth for the farmers not for the people
In Huron you know we've been fighting poverty for years and years and years and that's a
That's a demon that probably won't go away
In 1979 Carter's investigators found that Huron the largest town in the Westlands
Have become one of the poorest towns in California
The Spanish surname population of families were running 30% below the poverty level
Which is particularly striking in the context of zero unemployment
The the we couldn't find any evidence for unemployment in the region so that people were working these were people working
Very hard
How far be a below poverty wages
You know you can do a documentary and you can go out
Can say these people have a rough life they don't have a low income
But you can also live with them and work with them and know that they're happy people
Just like if you go to the third world the poorest people in the world
If they are
Adjusted and have
A way of life
That is fine way of life for them Mexican Americans
I found great work and and like the in some cases very well paying
Another case is pretty marginal but there's a way of life for them too driving a tractor is driving a tractor and it's outside
Better job than a lot of us have
For 2 weeks each
Bring in fall all the letters in America comes from the Westlands and every year enough cotton for a
Doing t-shirts my 1979
No place on Earth
I've been so changed
By the manipulation of water
Except in a few game Reser
Nearly all the valleys native fish in animals were gone
Much of the Sacramento River now irrigated crops
And the San Joaquin River sometimes flowed backwards
Chinook salmon were nearly extinct
The Crux of the
Salmon or people
No I'm sure people
Survive without salmon
But I don't think people
Survive without beans
Some potatoes
Using let
There was a run
A million to 2 million
I'm coming up in Sacramento River every year there were 21 canneries
In the Central Valley
There isn't any way to control the river
Without
And the salmon unfortun
Believe is one of the trade offs on the Sacramento River and on the Columbia River
I think it's worth it yes I think
They're substitutes for eating salmon
You can eat
In 1980
The Carter Administration was reviewing Growers water contracts
They were paying about
A quarter of what it cost to bring the water across California
President Carter running for re
Could have sent a strong message by questioning the price of water
Enforcing 168th and 11th
And demanding environmental changes in Western water policy
But suddenly
On the heels of a hostage crisis in Iran
Carter found himself in a race for his political life
Against Ronald reag
He turned to the San Joaquin Valley for campaign support
Carter and Congress chose not to change Western water policy
Need some money you'll land down there on one of those private Landings they have lunch for you walk out there $10,000 richer
And they buy another day
And that's what they're doing they're just playing for time
This is
You couldn't
But there was now public suspicion that something had
Gone terribly wrong amid the abundance
And an environmental Time Bomb was about to explode
Employees of the US fish and wildlife service have been doing this for months
Wildlife Refuge
For an individual who's been spending a lifetime trying to create habit
To
Try to move
The wild
Away from this habit that you've created
These traditions of the birds are very very difficult to
Impossible
Especially when once they've begun to nest
It was
It was a war zone out here
The fish and wildlife people refer to these mosquito fish
As little selenium tablets
See
From
Intensive
Farming and irrig
Deforming
Whatever tiny little
Museum pie
Use of
Nature were left
Runoff from Westlands Farms contain selenium
For years
Drainage had concentrated the selenium in the casterson ponds
Why would Bureau of Reclamation waited for a permit
To dump it into the San Francisco Bay and Delta
We went ahead with the Restless project
Or we saw the drainage problem
We thought we knew how to Sol
Probably thought the Kesterson Reservoir could be flushed on out
Delta we didn't have
Solid
So I made a
Steak by going ahead with Westlands at the time we did
But the problem begins on the farms and it winds up in the Refuge
Many young birds have been killed and deformed by high concentrations of selenium found in the
The very
Started features bills that were Twisted missing eyeballs
Bulges on the brain
Deformed feet
They remind me of the of the thalidomide babies that were over in in Europe
And his Mud Hens were up at this
Get it too much selenium and too much selenium
Exploded in her face
Bird deformities
What
Oliver
Attackers the proof they need that agriculture really is bad it does destroy the environment
Cuz we had some to form birds out there
Kesterson was approved
And we were the bad guys and it was really a turning point
And we would sit and struggle with
A photograph
Of a bird
Headline
On every newspaper and TV news every night you know about this crisis
At the end of irrigated agriculture in a million Acres
Going to go out of production
We cannot make a connection between
How do we solve this problem and how do we deal with this public
Crisis over here that was created
But for those mud
And but for those
Reservoir
Ah that plan eventually would have continued to creep on
But those are those Mud Hens
They really turned
The political history
Of other Central Valley Project
It was all adding up
Public anger at the
Congressional investigations in the water subsidies
Farm labor and salmon
And now the Last Straw
6 years of drought
Dust storms rake the valley
Trucks Bound for Market
Slammed into the biggest wreck in American history on Interstate 5
In the Westlands
Growers short on water
Let their fields go Barren and the Dust
Piled up waiting for strong winds to blow across the highway
Kind of moves us ahead
About
20 years in time
And all of a sudden
We have major shortages
Water was a lot like
That it was price responsive
And we we really had to do was attack
Subsidy and we became a nice Target
Subsidy issue fashioned in there there was a
All kinds of sex
Sexy political things that ways to beat us
Big slow moving Target
The areas of the country
Which have huge population growth on limited water resources are going to have to change the structure of their water usage
Going to have to become more
Conservation Orient
George Bush on the road on a roll he told the Valley Farmers
I don't believe we need the federal government
Getting into the water rights business
Bush was losing to Bill Clinton
Just before the election he signed a popular reform law in hopes of gaining electoral V
And for the first time in 50 years
Return water
Into the salmon stream
You were going to have to now pay for that water
And if you had to now pay for that water
You'd have to take into consideration other concerns
In terms of how you use that water how efficient you are the kinds of crops that you have to grow
When the law was changed when the project was redirected it was
You're a huge train wreck and
Cuz we've been chugging along doing great 50 years reliability project working good all this very stable farmers were not worried
In California until the drought because it was reliable
Now we've got new contracts and our water costs have gone from 350 which is a great deal for 40 years
To
5:45 an acre foot overnight
Huge swings in cost
The water has gotten more expensive
But really with a shortage of water and all we're paying
We need to make sure we
Don't use any more than absolutely
Expensive
But we're
I
This is got to be one of the most efficient uses of water there is
But it belongs to us don't it
The big canal
The tax
Did I see something wrong
In the year since the reform law there has been
Been a fragile peace
But the Great Central Valley will never be the same
Nearly all the corporate Farms have gone along with some smaller Farms
Native birds and Chinook salmon
Have begun a very slow comeback
The large Growers Who Remain
Are among the most productive and water efficient in the country
Producing more
With less water
No one will ever know
For the thousands of small farm
Could have done the same
Water
Is the essence of our existence without it there can be no
Civilizations began next
To order
But as populations grow
Especially an arid regions there is not enough to go around
I'm
Decisions about water have been
Guided by a very simple formula
Which
Estimate human demands for water
And build a new water project to meet it
And that equation was simple and it worked as long as water was abund
But it's not working anymore because water is becoming scarce
Concrete dams have dominated our management of water in the past 50 years
Dams tested and built to master the power of nature
The story of water has been the story of controlling it
38,000 large dams have been built in all dams to store water
And control plugs games for irrigation and hydroelectricity
Dams that have inundated canyons and drained wetland
Now
The damn building era in the United States is coming to a close the best sites are taken
The economic and environmental cost
Are too high
And Americans are beginning to turn
To conservation
But developing countries
To provide water and power for growing populations still covered these engineering Marvels
They sent their best and brightest to be trained by the Bureau of Reclamation
Builders of the super dams of the American West
Right after Hoover Dam
Much completed the world recognized that a great achievement is occur
Your Reclamation was bes
And we ended up as the training center
For young Engineers send here from Thailand
Turkey
Ethiopia all around the world
India
Was an example of
Everywhere I went in India they thought I was the second coming of the Buddha
More than any other Nation
India has staked its future on large Dam
In 1963
Prime minister nairu predicted that dams would become the temples of Modern India
Today
Have created electricity and supplied irrigation to feed the hungry subcontinent
But the dams have taken a heavy human to
Some 20 million people have lost their homes
In recent years a controversy has erupted over the damning of the name of the
I told my Nichols at Freddy's
Funny I'll go in the club
They look like
The weather
What about
Despite the damning of the narmada
Protesters have gone on math hunger strikes
Led by Major pad car
Members of the movement even threatened to drown themselves
The Verizon flood waters
Construction has stop
While the government reviews the project
So far
60 Villages have been inundated
It is unclear how India will proceed
A hemisphere away on the border between Argentina and
Paraguay
Biologists worry that the reservoir created by the dam will cause an outbreak of schistosomiasis
What's on call the disease of hydroelectric dams in the tropics
Feels like these breed in the stagnant reservoirs
Releasing a parasitic worm that penetrates human skin damaging the liver and spleen
People are not the only ones at risk
Has this region is flooded
70 kinds of mammals and 300 bird species will lose their home
Can a region where rainforest habitat is rapidly disappearing
Efforts to rescue some of the larger animals rarely succeed
Many will die from the stresses of capture
Where the damn building era is really going a gangbusters now is in countries like Indonesia
China
Malaysia Brazil
Other South American countries Chile
Some of the
Most beautiful River
It
The planet I know being
Turned in the res
And some of the biggest dam
Ever build bigger than anything but we've
Are being
Southern countries like Brazil and China
Want to build three gorgeous Dam
The world's largest hydroelectric project
Eventually Rising 600 ft High
And over a mile wide
The demo create an enormous Lake
That will stretch nearly
400 Mi Upstream
China's leaders say three gorgeous will fuel its industrial Rev
And save millions of people from frequent floods along the Yankee River
What is the Finish is going to be the largest time in the world it was Supply 1/10 of your electricity for China
Critics of three gorgeous say the project will create a 30 billion
Dollar Bo
Because
Multiple build up behind the dance
The project will flood the nation's most beautiful region
As famous in China as the Grand Canyon is in the US
Over
Million people in Riverside villages will be displaced
Even the World Bank longest supporter of large dams has withdrawn from Three Gorges
But China says it will go ahead and find its own financing
In late 1993
Dan beard
Then chief of the US Bureau of Reclamation
Withdrew his agency's technical support for Three Gorges
There's no better example
Of project we shouldn't be involved
Country gorgeous Dam
We've moved away from Water Project
Construction in the United States and I
For
Continue to be involved in the largest
Damn construction project in the world
There are better
Easier and cheaper way
Solve
The problems of
Control and
The three gorgeous amp
Moving from large construction projects
To a culture of conservation
Requires a major change in the way people think about water
And many developing countries face staggering problems
I both water quality
And water
Mexico
Struggling now to provide water for 20 million people
Predicted to grow by another 10 million in the next decade
Just wear the water will come from
Remains an open question
Originally built on a system of five lakes
Mexico City began its history rich in water
He has text once
Holding Fields along these canals
This is all that remains of those Lakes
Today
3/4 of Mexico City's population enjoys modern plumbing
And plenty of water for drinking showers and sanitation
But
Brawling Shanty towns
Migrants from rural areas
Water
Or even the most
Basic human needs
Mexico City faces
One of the most difficult
Challenges of any urban area in the world with regard to water
18 to 20 million people living in
I'm very very densely populated area
The next best news source of water is a thousand meters below the city
They're very dependent on groundwater and already over pumping
That groundwater
On the order of 50 to 80
Percent
The city's ancient
Cathedral is sinking because of the overpumping built after the Spanish Conquest
Dramatically on one side
Wires joists metal clamps all support the weekend
Some sections of the city are thinking 12 in a year
One quarter of
University's water must be pumped in from 100 miles away
With Antiquated pipes damaged by subsidence and earthquakes
The city loses almost a third of its water to leaks which is a common problem
Around the world for cities with aging pipes
Still celebrates its long love affair with water
But there's a terrible irony in the way
And poor people get their water for the well to do
Piped in water is cheap and plentiful for the poor water is
Very expensive and hard to come by
Circle City has a growing population
A lot of people are coming in from outside to the city and
For the city it's very difficult to provide them with services
In the
Where people don't get much of the water supply which is the poor part of the population they get the water
The
Amount of what they earn a day
For this water
In this new District
Residents were promised piped in Water by local politicians
But so far
They have received no services
Like many of her neighbors
Guadalupe Sanchez Lopez is forced to store her family's water supply in rainbows
She lives with her children in a two-room house with no running water
I'm connected to any sewer
The toilet represents a hope for the future
It sits over a hole in the ground
For two barrels of water from a local company Sanchez pay
Five pesos a quarter of her family's income of $4 a day
Diner
Para comparison
El problema principal
Elephanta de agua de quada distribution Delaware principalent
Young children are at the greatest risk
Child mortality here is 10 times higher than in wealthy sections of the city
And just down the street sewage and Industrial Waste run raw in one of Mexico City
The main canals a common problem in many parts of the developing world
Following the recent outbreak of color that claimed lives all over Latin America
Mexico City launched a campaign urging people to boil their drinking water and to wash their hands after going to
Into the bathroom
80% of illnesses in developing countries can be traced to unsafe water
And poor Sanitation
Over a billion people in the world don't have
Have access even to basic drinking water and sanitation requirements
Many of these countries are growing in population very very fast
Last many African countries Middle Eastern countries
Their population
Will double within a generation
I'm
Supplying water to meet
The drinking water needs the food needs the industrial needs of a population growing that fast is extremely difficult
And many of these countries are already
Water short
The nations of the Middle East
Are already hitting the limits of their renewable Water Supplies
With populations predicted to double in 30 years the Israelis Jordan
For urban and Industrial use with little freshwater to grow food
These people's realized that if they don't cooperate to share their limited Water Resources
It may mean War
Israel has had long running disputes with Jordan Syria and Lebanon over
For the rights
Hostilities between the Israelis and the Palestinians over land
Have run high for decades but less well known is the fact that Israel draws one quarter
Water from the occupied territories
Resolving water disputes will require not only diplomacy but new technologies that can make
Make the most of the Region's limited Supply
Israel is building hundreds of Apartments blocks to accommodate a large
Effects of immigrants from the former Soviet Union 700,000 people in 3 years
To meet it's growing needs Israel is depending more and more on recycled
We recycle reuse
Our dirty shirts
We la
You have to learn how to launder
As more fresh water is diverted to cities
Recycled water is the only source that actually grows with population
It's the shadow of the supply Israel now Rec
= 2/3 of its water
This facility handles the Wastewater of Seven Cities
Reclaimed water gets used in Cooling in sanitation system
No not intended for human consumption the final product
Does me drinking water standings
Recycled water is also
To irrigate
Now at first the farmers were
Farmers are usually pretty conservative
But as time went on and particularly during the drought in 1991
Wastewater became a very sought after Resort why
Because when the Sweetwater sources were in short supply
The Wastewater was there
And the farmers were clamoring to connect up
To the Wastewater we use the project
In the blistering heat of the negative
Israeli Farmers have created an agricultural Miracle pioneering the use of
Irrigation they have double their harvests with the same amount of water
Perforated tubes deliver water directly to the roots of the plants avoid
Wedding evaporation losses
Moisture sensors tell Farmers precisely when their crops need water drip techn
Apology can save a third of the water used in spray methods however
Tell us that irrigation has periods like
In the life of a married couple
There is the honeymoon between the irrigator
And the
And this happens
In the beginning like most animals
And after some decad
There is
Increasing the deterioration of the land
As a result of irrigation South brought in by irrigation water concentr
In the soil
Damaging it's fertility
Story for example is
The federal Crescent Iraq of these days
Will thousands of fields ago
Irrigation was used
But the land deteriorated and some of it is as still not recovered from this bad experience
With human irrigation similar processes are now starting to be seen in every IR
Get the direction all over the world
From California
Show the Mediterranean region to Australia China India and South America
One Salt build up
They must be flushed out
With even more water
So over the course of generations
There are limits to how much water can be cons
The power to remove salt from ocean water has long been a dream
Promising almost Limitless water for human needs
Desalinated water is already serving some urban populations those that can afford a high price
But it's unlikely in the foreseeable future to be cheap enough for you in agriculture
The problem with desalination is that it's very energy intensive it takes a lot of
Energy to remove salt from water
So at the moment
Most of the desalination that's happening in the world is in the Persian Gulf
Saudi Arabia Kuwait
United Arab Emirates they account for about
Half of all the desalination that's happening even though they have only a tiny share
Of the world's population
They're essentially turning oil into water and they're among the few countries that can afford to do that
Disputes over water in the Middle East go back
A long way
According to the Bible the wells in the land of the Philistines were called hatred and
In Gaza and on the West Bank of the
Gordon River
Israel provides piped in water to Israeli settlers
Wild Palestinian citizens have received a more limited Supply
When it comes to military occupation
And famous they don't go together
If the current situation continues
I see the Palestinian
Honey
And what that can
Already we see signs of
Where kidney fail
As a result of
Freshwater
And unsafe and polluted water
This cannot continue
This is
A recipe
For dis
In most Palestinian homes
Rainwater is collected and stored in cisterns below ground
Each system
$10,00
An expensive investment for families who only earn half that in a year
Is Hitler in the West Bank consume seven times more
Not going to see me
End
And in Gaza they consum
14 times more
This is a source
In
Which is causing
Money for the students to ask why
We need to have water
Our children doing water exactly like crazy chicken
Of all the people in the Middle East the Palestinians are those
Most
And I as an Israeli would like to say that
Without getting into the amount
Of water that are
Discussion
It should be in Israel's interest
To see you
Did the Palestinian
Get a fair deal
And get enough water so they feel comfortable for the future
It's in Israel's interest to live in peace with its neighbors
I think the potential for conflict is going to persist until we see water sharing agreements that
Buy the water equitably in each of the major river basins in the Middle East and elsewhere
We're beginning to see countries realize that they have
Benefits to gain from from cooperating and
If they continue to see that we could see water
And water scarcity become a motivation for peace rather than War
Half a world away
The tug of war over water goes on in the Arid American West
There's a lust for water here that borders on obsession
Get free time
They had for the nearest water they can find rivers pools
Artificial Lakes
There are no natural lakes here
Water from the Colorado River has transformed the desert into the fastest growing
Region of the country
10 major dams stop up the river
And Canal siphon off water for irrigation and growing cities
Most of these water projects were constructed before the 1960s and seventies
When things begin to change
Project
Before
We're built with
Almost no environmental consideration at all
And then finally The Endangered Species Act the National Environmental Policy I came along
And those allow
The public into the
And then
Began to get out
The best sites have been taken
And so the newer dance were
Much more expensive for the equivalent amount of water that you might get out
And essentially as the country
A master greater and greater Federal
People began to say wait a minute
Why are we building billion dollar dams when I have to do
Conserve some water and you can get just as much with conservation as you would with the supply
The city of Denver was forced to put these new realities to the test
In 1982 the water board filed application to build two forks
River
In the midst of a growth boom
Future
What city officials didn't anticipate was an overwhelming protest
From environmental groups fisherman biologist
An ordinary citizens
It really was the last dance
Of the dinosaurs
It was
Developed in an ER
When we thought
About water only is its value and being taken from the Stream
To supply
And to supply agriculture
We're now in the mode where we think about water in its natural course
Is valuable in its own right
Two books damn was to be located 25 miles
From Denver on the South Platte River it was flood a 28 mile
Richard land
Including Cheeseman Canyon
And a prime trout Fishery
You can't understand
What a damn does and put a reservoir is unless you've been there before
The construction
And if you go out to two forks what you find is the narrowing of a
Can
A very efficient place to put in a
60 story high cement
But it is a place you don't want to lose
And people went there
And they spoke out in different ways and said we don't want to lose that place
There was more than Cheeseman Canyon at stake
The Platte River flows north into Nebraska
Biologist worried that two forks stand with pirate the Platte rivers flow
Strangling with land habitat for migratory bird
All around us right now we're hearing the sound of the Santo cranes that visit the plot
Every Spring as part of the
Greatest migration of cranes that occurs on face of the Earth
They gather on this River in numbers that are truly astounding half a million Santo cranes
Rather hear each spring if you're in central Nebraska
The perfect combination of flowing water a shallow River Fields of food for them to eat
And in this Gathering we have
One of the greatest spectacles in North America
And people come here from all over the country and all around the world to see this event because it's unmatched anywhere else
Bands of Empire not
Upstream in the area
It's flooded by a reservoir
But
Strength throughout the entire system where
The blockage of flow
Alters the way the river flows Downstream and can alter the habitats of differently
The Platte River used to be over a mile wide
Today diversions for irrigation have reduced
Flow by 70%
Squeezing migratory Birds into smaller and smaller areas of habitat
Pounds and communities along the
Have finally come to the realization that the kinds of clothes they need staying drinking water supplies
And to just generally provide for a healthy human environment
A very similar to the kinds of clothes that we've been saying are needed to sustain an
So in a very real sense
What happens to the cranes
Is indication of what's happening to us and the human Community here on the flat
Still the question remain
How to provide for Denver's growth
As the debate over two forks rage done Denver spent 45
But at the 11th Hour
All in all
We were able to demonstrate
That you could Supply
20% more water than two forks
The cost
Two
And
The environmental damage
When
Cities have expensive capital projects to look at you can almost always demonstrate conservation
Makes more sense
Building a new project
Hot water for our cities and hydropower is important but so are Wild River
And we feel that as a people and we feel what a river really can be
Be a place of magic and mystery and beauty
And we've made up our mind now that we are going to
Keep some Rivers Wild
Both
What they can give to us
As a people
And and also to the animals in the plants that depend upon them and also I think out of some ultimate respect
Back to the river itself
Denver now had to look
Within
To figure out how to meet it it's water needs without a new source of water
And what Denver found is that
A gallon of water saved through conservation and efficiency is just as good as a gallon supplied from a new dam
In fact it's better because
It doesn't involve
Destroying a beautiful place like Cheesman Canyon
Denver has since been encouraging conservation City
It turned out that
Just installing water meters made homeowners more conscious of how much they
The water board raised water rates
And now gives cash payments to businesses that adopt efficiency measures
Program that will pay a business
A free time what they would pay us for the water if they save that water permanent
Now it's a one-time payment of up to $20,000
That business installs water saving Hardware that will save us
The deal water in the long run we will pay them
City Ice was one of the first local companies to undergo a water audit
The biggest item was to try to do something with process water that was coming off our ice making oper
Reduction in our
Water from the ice making process was reclaimed for use as a cooling agent in refrigeration
Many businesses could cut their water use in half
By reclaiming water for Rin cycles and cooling systems
One of the best ways homeowners can conserve is to try a landscaping idea pioneer
Denver
It's called xeriscape
And it involves
Of selecting plant
Trees and ground cover native to the region or that require only small amounts of water
Like Buffalo
Overwatering the lawn is
Single biggest household waste of water
We've got to move towards pricing water at somewhere near its value
We currently give it away
In fact sometimes we pay people
What is it's ludicrous that the most fundamental resource that we have
The one that is
Fundamental to life
Is a resource in which we're giving it away
We waste water in ways that you can't imagine
Does this completely modernize dishwashing every housewife in the land will answer yes
The American dream of the 1950s was to have all the modern conveniences
Washers disposals and dish
Washers all running on unlimited supplies of water
Today
The average American family of four uses 300 gallons of water a day
Enough to fill this bathtub
In Tucson Arizona
At the Casa del Agra or House of water
A conventional home has been retrofitted with water saving devices
Is he just how much an average family could
Glenn and Catherine friends have lived here for 10 years
Raising their family and monitoring every drop of water
You're the cost of Delaware house we use about half of what a typical home uses
That water is portable water that I'm talking about we also use
Water that is harvested from the roof which is rain water
Can we use gray water which is the water from the kitchen sinks
The bathtub the shower and the washing machine
Fixtures have been equipped with low flow shower heads and faucets
Recycled gray water and rainwater collected from the roof
Irrigate the family zeroscape garden
Studies show that the best way to save water indoors
Is to replace the old 6 gallon per
Toilet with a new 1.6 gallon
Saving 21 gallons per person per day
Well what is toilets have been used here
And as a result of the research that we did here on those toilet
Local plumbing codes have been adopted and now the National Standard has been adopted
For the use of the 1.6 gallon for flush toilets
Casa de lagua is just one example of innovative programs around the world that are proving
Conservation can make a big difference
But households use only 10% of water worldwide
And industries claim only 25%
Agriculture uses the greatest share
65% worldwide
And even more
Here in the Southwest
Desert Wasteland
How you
Imported water
Today
California uses more than it's legal share of the Colorado
Someday it may have to give up that water
So more and more
California is looking toward conservation
Historically we viewed water conservation as something that we do in the middle of a drought
And once Drive is over we forget about
It can't be that way anymore water conservation
You can make a tremendous
The water system if you will is probably the most inefficient system
We have
For any
In California's Imperial Valley
Irrigation water from the Colorado River
Is brought in by canals managed by the Bureau of Reclamation
And paid for by us taxpayers
Farming here is a billion dollar business
All they pay is the cost of delivery
Dating back to the 19th century
Water rights in this Valley are tied to the land
Since water is so cheap
There has been little incentive to invest in conservation
The Imperial Irrigation District slurps off about
20% of it
To irrigate 400,000 acres of land
Very permeable land
Scorching clim
So
Very high water to
A lot of people complained about that for a long time is perhaps the ultimate example of ineffic
The IID now is beginning to think about selling some of this
And I personally think that's a good idea
Los Angeles is really paying
For the efficiency improvements
And then paying for the water as well
Like this pump back system that recaptures surface runoff
Paid for by the Metropolitan water district of Southern California
Mwd gets to keep the water saved
And the farmer gets to keep the system
And you water marketing deals
Farmers are beginning to sell their water to cities like San Diego
It's a good way for thirsty cities to find new supp
It can create windfall profits
Or landowner selling water that's been subsidized at taxpayer expense
The billionaire Bass Brothers of Texas recently bought 30,000 acres here
And hope to Market some of the water that goes with their land
We got to stop giving away water as if it was a free good
You have Farm
Wasting water and you have millions of people
I need additional
Well it doesn't take a gen
Figure out
Just going to be in a very short period of time
Agriculture accounts for the Lion's Share of the world's water and a very large share on the order of 80 to
5%, and most of the western us
So this is really the the biggest pool of water that that we have
Saving even a tiny share of water in agriculture can free up a lot of water
To meet new Urban
Cities like Los Angeles are looking for ways to reduce the
What's the water they use and to reclaim and reuse water before they dispose of it
The Metropolitan water district works with local groups like mothers of East Los Angeles to encourage
Low flow toilets
Started by one of Gutierrez the organization is now run by her daughter Elsa Lopez
We have given approximately about $85,000 toilet
And that will be a savings of 7.6 billion gallons of water
A year
People bring in their old water guzzling toilets and exchange them for the new low flow models
Mayabahoya Independence
And the mothers of East LA get $25 for each old-fashioned toilet they collect
The freeways the new toilet save the city 8 million gallons a day
We're really excited about having the water conservation program and the results I have come from it
Saving all those gallons of water
And
Saving the community money
And bring it in jobs for them
What the shop up right over here
Each year Lopez takes teenagers from East LA 300 miles
Kimono
So they can see where some of their water comes from
It's an unusual Mountain Lake rimmed with strange natural structures made of lime
They're called to the towers
How does a tufa
Some of this is always a thousand years
But a lot of it's really young 75 to 200 years
And yet it's above ground
And two for only for
Underwater
So you know that the lake has dropped pretty quickly
The Lakes level had drained down
Because water from its feeder streams was being diverted to Los Angeles
But a state water board decision in 1994
Stops the diversions
And now it's waters are slowly Rising
Pour out the movie the excess water system
I think what we all realize is that there are mono Lakes at the ends of all of our taps or these special places
Of our water suppl
Conservation and recycling will become even more important to Los Angeles
The loss of water from Mono Lake
Has increased the need to conserve
The city also knows
That it will eventually have to give up some of the Colorado River water on which it depends
Water that belongs to
Upstream
And by treaty
A portion of the Colorado's water belongs to Mexico
There's a very fundamental problem with the Colorado River
Or there was a very rainy year
And then all the politicians sat down to divide up the amount of water
And they made
A very large mistake
They divided up more water than they've ever had since
It hasn't rained as much and haven't had
Much water
Since The Times They divide it up
So what you have
You've overallocated that River
You've given away more water
Then you really have
Have been described as thirsty
Dogs fighting over a damn sponge
This is one of the few Wetlands remaining in the Colorado Delta
Just South of the Border
It gives
Small idea of what the Delta used to be like before dams
In 1922
The Great American conservationist Aldo Leopold pay the visit to the Colorado Delta and wrote
About it in The Marvelous essay in sand County Almanac is his Masterworks when he found there was
Price of paradise
For wildlife
Jaguar
Cougars bobcat
Team with water
It's so ironic that in that year
The Colorado River compact the sign and that
Began shutting off the flow of water
And it's essentially a dead zone
Everything that Leopold saw
Is gone
Vehicle describe the Colorado Delta
As a milk and honey wilderness
Full of 100 green lagoons
The region provided habitat for species
Live mostly in zoos today
Endangered creatures like the jaguarundi
A Mexican wolf
Today
The Colorado Delta
Has been transformed into miles of dried out salt
The river no longer makes it to the
California
It's historic destination
Virtually nothing is reaching the delta
In an average year and so the ecosystem has been
Completely changed and
The native
Communities that have relied on this ecosystem and this water for thousands of years
Are now suffering and very much in Decline themselves
Fisheries in this region are in severe trouble
In part because of overfishing but also because diversions of water Upstream
Damage the Delta spawning grounds
The cocoa pot Indians who live in the Delta once had a thriving culture of fishing
In Riverbank farming
No matter because
Their way of life
Is now in jeopardy
Weeds choke the river behind their Village
It's barely a foot deep
Animated
Tomorrow for tomorrow I want to make the skeleton do another of this camera customer
No Palawan radio
Jose don't leave Animal Hospital
Bella pesca
Porque Pacino
Yeah they already talk almost a
Practice out for La Cristiano
Today for their household needs
Coca power reliant on water brought in by the barrel
They say bathing is basically
Has for fishing the cocoa must now haul their boat
40 miles to get to the saltwater channel of the Gulf of California
And they bought fuel for both the trucks and the boats it becomes a costly trip
But it's mainly the young men who go out in the boat
These Waters were once Rich fishing grounds and fish
But on this day
They catch nothing
Finally after many hours of effort they give up
It is a very long trip IND
The community's young people still hold fast to the tribes identity as River people
Fake chosen the name pescad
For fisherman for the soccer team
Dear future is clouded by the problems with the Colorado River
When are y'all went right now
You know what I hope
You everything I don't want nothing
They Don't Really consumer Rio Colorado
So I thought I would stop by
Perhaps
If the true potential of conservation could be realized
And the benefits distributed fairly there was some day be enough water for everyone
To restore the coral River delt
Will take a lot
It's probably impossible to go back to what it used to be Los
A lot of things that can be done with just allowing somebody to come
Particular times
Of the year
A good important lesson is when we look at other Elders we should now carefully
Look at the environmental impact
The diamond on irrigation project will have we should not repeat what we did with the
In the end we may need a new water ethic
And I think that says it's important now to begin
Sharing
With each other as well as with nature
There's no proverb that goes something like
The Frog does not drink up the pond
In which it lives and I think it's a very simple
Wisdom but it really
Captures the challenge I think that we're facing which is
How we're going to meet our growing human needs for water
And still live in Bal
With the ecosystems
That support all life